<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons shewing the necessity of reformation of the publick [brace]1. doctrine, 2. worship, [double brace] 3. rites and ceremonies, 4. church-government, and discipline, reputed to be (but indeed, not) established by law. Humbly offered to the serious consideration of this present Parliament. By divers ministers of sundry counties in England.</title>
            <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E764_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205206</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864637</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864637</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116869</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77860)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 117:E764[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons shewing the necessity of reformation of the publick [brace]1. doctrine, 2. worship, [double brace] 3. rites and ceremonies, 4. church-government, and discipline, reputed to be (but indeed, not) established by law. Humbly offered to the serious consideration of this present Parliament. By divers ministers of sundry counties in England.</title>
                  <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ja: Cottrel.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLX. [1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Cornelius Burges.</note>
                  <note>The words "1. doctrine, 2. worship," are enclosed in brackets and the words "3. rites .. church-government," are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116869:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASONS SHEWING the Neceſsity of Reformation of the Publick
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Doctrine,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Worſhip,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Rites and Ceremonies,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Church-Government,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> and <hi>Diſcipline, Reputed</hi> to be (but indeed, not) <hi>Eſtabliſhed by LAW.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly offered to the Serious Conſideration of this preſent PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>By divers <hi>Miniſters</hi> of ſundry <hi>Counties</hi> in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 COR. 13.8.</hi>
               </bibl> For, we can do nothing againſt the truth; but, for the truth.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by JA: COTTREL. MDCLX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116869:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, THE Lords and Commons ASSEMBLED in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is far from our thoughts to oppoſe, or diſparage Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox <hi>Doctrine,</hi> a well-compoſed <hi>Liturgy, Rites</hi> for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and order, <hi>Ordination</hi> of Miniſters, Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Epiſcopacie,</hi> or due <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> We are for all theſe, with Truth; and, againſt rigid Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which may debar a Chriſtian of any liberty allowed him by Christ.</p>
            <p>Nor do we offer any Polemical Diſcourſe, or Theological Debates proper for a Divinity-School, or Synod: but onely, what we humbly conceive more ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to a Parliament. Our work, chiefly, is, out of thoſe Laws, which we, as Miniſters, are bound to take ſpecial notice of; and, out of thoſe <hi>Books</hi> ſaid to be by thoſe Laws ſettled; to make out theſe two things. First, that (ſo far as we can apprehend) neither the <hi>Articles of Religion,</hi> the <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Com. Prayer,</hi> or <hi>Ordination,</hi> the <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of Biſhops, claimed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>17 Car. 1.</hi> nor ſo much as their <hi>Being,</hi> as <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſithence; nor thoſe <hi>Canons</hi> ſo much contended for, are indeed eſtabliſhed by Law. Secondly, that none of theſe, as they now ſtand, ought to be confirmed and ſetled. But, all, with ſubmiſsion. And this we truſt ſhall not be cenſured as Eccentrick. For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit we acknowledge the learned in the Law to be far more able in matter of Law, touching theſe things; yet, ſeeing every Subject is to inform himſelf of all ſuch Laws as more eſpecially concern his own calling, we hope it will not be
<pb facs="tcp:116869:2"/>judged an extravagancie, or preſumption in us, to produce thoſe Laws which more nearly concern all of our Function.</p>
            <p>Of this, we apprehend ſome neceſsity. <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe it is already too ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, that too many (notwithſtanding all pretences of Moderation) do alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fly higher than ever; ſome, in aſſerting <hi>Arminianiſme</hi> to be <hi>the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of England,</hi> thinking thereby to force all to imbrace it; ſome, in ſtickling for the <hi>Liturgy</hi> commonly uſed; ſome, ſtill holding up <hi>ſole Ordination</hi> by, and <hi>ſole Juriſdiction</hi> of Biſhops; and, all <hi>Canons,</hi> not onely made in <hi>England,</hi> but in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, (if not repugnant to our Laws;) labouring to poſſeſs the people that all theſe are ſettled by Law, and therefore to be continued, and <hi>impoſed,</hi> without alteration; and that all who ſeek a <hi>Reformation</hi> of them, do oppoſe and violate the eſtabliſhed Laws. <hi>2.</hi> Becauſe if men go on in ſuch ways, and prevail therein, it is to be feared, that, in ſhort time, every Minister of different judgement, (how able, godly, and uſeful ſoever) will be put, not onely out of his preſent place, but out of the Ministry alſo, as it hath already too often happened. And indeed, it can hardly be found in any age ſince the <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> that where Kings have not curbed the violence of Biſhops, they have ever ſharply perſecuted all that threw off Popery; which Perſecutions uſually produced Confuſions in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. For prevention whereof, we humbly beſeech all Noble Spirits, and faithful prudent Patriots, to look back upon the Mutinies, Inſurrections &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, in <hi>Edw. 6.</hi> his time, occaſioned by fomenting, and not moderating the furious Zeal even of thoſe that were most countenanced by that pious King; which notwithſtanding the Act of <hi>1. Edw. 6.1.</hi> made many to flee ſo high, as exaſperated the other ſide ſo far, as that it put ſeveral parts of the Kingdom into Combustion. Nor will thoſe rivers of blood ſhed in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> days, by recalling the Biſhops and others formerly deprived, and giving way to their wonted tyranny, in the height thereof, be forgotten, while ought of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion remaineth. Nor will it be unſeaſonable to reflect upon the throwing out of many worthy Ministers in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> reign; and, of many moe, under K. <hi>James.</hi> For, that Noble King, immediately after his coming to the Crown, was ſo plyed by Biſhops, that, notwithſtanding the <hi>Conference at Hampton Court,</hi> the Prelatical Party prevailed ſo far, that the <hi>Liturgy</hi> (then much complained of) remained in greateſt part, and in the most mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial points, unreformed: to which, they all were compelled to <hi>ſubſcribe:</hi> which had never been required before; and many Illegal <hi>Canons</hi> were made, and inforced ſo far, that within the ſpace of two years (as was credibly reported) <hi>70</hi> Ministers were deprived, <hi>113</hi> not ſuffered to preach; and, about <hi>94</hi> more,
<pb facs="tcp:116869:3"/>were under <hi>Canonical Admonition,</hi> the next door to Deprivation. The carrying on of all which, together with the countenancing of <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> formerly declared againſt, by that Learned King <hi>James</hi> (witneſs his promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Dort</hi>) did ſo much, and ſo generally offend, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate, that, after many thouſands were compelled to leave their native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, <hi>to dwell in Meſech, and to take up their habitations in the tents of Kedar;</hi> others were drawn on to engage ſo deeply in the publick differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, (which, as to matters of Religion, were occaſioned by the continuing of the former corruptions, and by thoſe <hi>Canons,</hi> of <hi>1639.</hi>) as produced all thoſe horrid and bloody effects, which we abhor to mention, and tremble to remember.</p>
            <p>May it therefore pleaſe your Wiſdoms, Piety, and Goodneſs, to procure a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of all theſe things, after the example of the <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>3.4. Edw. 6.</hi> and, to call ſome of the moſt moderate and able perſons of every different par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to aſsiſt therein; and thereupon to ſettle all the things of God in a ſolid and moderate way, that all Ordinances of Christ may be reſtored to their priſtine Purity, all Chriſtians reduced <hi>to the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace:</hi> and, in the mean time, nothing to be impoſed which may grieve or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thoſe who ſhall be careful not to diſturb the Publick Peace. In order to which ends, we humbly recommend to your Noble and Pious thoughts, that of the Apostle; <hi>Let your moderation be known to all men; the LORD is at hand.</hi> For this, and for your Honours,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servants ſhall ever pray.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116869:3"/>
            <head>REASONS SHEWING The Neceſsity of Reformation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. <hi>Of DOCTRINE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Publick <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as it is commonly received, and inſiſted upon, is ſaid to be contained in the 39 <hi>Articles, agreed upon by the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, and the whole Clergy, in the Convocation holden at</hi> London, <hi>in the year</hi> 1562. Thoſe <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> are taken to be ratified and confirmed by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> in 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 12. Which <hi>Act</hi> provideth, <hi>That no perſon ſhall be admitted to any Benefice with Cure, except he ſhall firſt have ſubſcribed the ſaid Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in preſence of the</hi> Ordinary, <hi>and publickly read the ſame in the Pariſh Church of that Benefice whereof he ſhall have Cure, with declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his unfeigned aſſent thereunto, within two moneths after his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>upon default hereof, to be</hi> ipſofacto, <hi>immediately deprived.</hi> And, if any Eccleſiaſtical Perſon ſhall <hi>adviſedly maintain, or affirm any Doctrine contrary or repugnant to any of the ſaid Articles;</hi> and being convented, <hi>ſhall perſiſt therein, or not revoke his errour,</hi> or, <hi>after revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> return again to it, he ſhall be <hi>deprived of his Eccleſiaſtical Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> This is the effect of that <hi>Statute,</hi> as to this Point.</p>
               <p>But theſe <hi>Articles</hi> are both <hi>Doubtful,</hi> and <hi>Defective.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1. <hi>Doubtful.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe, it appears not that they were all, or any of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Parliament in the 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> for as much as they are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116869:4"/>in expreſly inſerted, nor ſo much as their <hi>number;</hi> but onely the <hi>Title</hi>-Page of them mentioned. Nor is it known where the Original is enrolled.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Of thoſe 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> there were 36 of them ſet forth (yet not ratified by <hi>Parliament</hi>) in <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. his reign: the other were added by the <hi>Convocation,</hi> in <hi>An.</hi> 1562.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the Books of <hi>Articles</hi> now printed, and ever ſince 10 <hi>Caroli</hi> 1. there is a Declaration of that his late Majeſty prefixed thereunto, by the advice and procurement of the then Biſhops, (after <hi>Arminianiſm</hi> began to perk, and to be openly preached by the riſing Party) to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. That thoſe <hi>Articles</hi> contain <hi>the true Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>agreeable to Gods Word:</hi> all therefore, are <hi>required to continue in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform Profeſſion thereof;</hi> and, <hi>the leaſt difference from them, prohibited.</hi> 2. That <hi>the Biſhops and Clergy, from time to time in Convocation, upon their humble deſire, ſhould have licence under the</hi> Broad
<note n="*" place="margin">This ſhews who did pen it.</note> Seal, <hi>to deliberate of, and to do all ſuch things, as being made plain by them, and aſſented unto by his then Majeſty, ſhall concern the ſetled continuance of the ſaid Doctrine</hi> (as well as <hi>Diſcipline) then eſtabliſhed; from which no variying or deparing in the leaſt degree, ſhould be endured.</hi> 3. That all <hi>curious ſearch, and diſputes,</hi> touching any points contained therein, be <hi>laid aſide, and ſhut up in Gods Promiſes,</hi> as <hi>generally</hi> ſet forth, and in the <hi>general meaning of theſe Articles.</hi> And, <hi>that no man ſhall either print or preach, to draw any Article aſide any way,</hi> nor <hi>put his own ſenſe or Comment</hi> upon it, <hi>but ſhall take it in the Literal and Grammatical ſenſe of it.</hi> This <hi>Declaration</hi> is publiſhed with the ſaid <hi>Articles,</hi> by <hi>Command.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If this be ſtill continued, and confirmed, then all theſe ſad Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences muſt needs follow:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That no Miniſter ſhall have ſo much liberty to interpret any one of thoſe <hi>Articles,</hi> as is not onely allowed, but required of him, in his <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> to expound the Word of God it ſelf. But this is a notorious truth, that after that <hi>Declaration</hi> was printed and publiſhed, as alſo a <hi>Proclamation</hi> to the ſame effect, iſſued, thoſe of the Prelatical Party had their Spies every where to ſee who durſt to preach a word againſt any <hi>Arminian</hi> Tenet; or, to explain any one <hi>Article,</hi> as not making for, but againſt any of thoſe Opinions. If any were found ſo to do, he was ſure to be Convented, for breach of the Kings <hi>Declaration</hi> and <hi>Proclamation;</hi> yea, ſome have been brought into the <hi>High Commiſſion-Court,</hi> for this very cauſe. While in the mean time, that other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty took liberty to vent and preach up thoſe points, without controul. Which no <hi>Anti-Arminians</hi> durſt call into queſtion; for that the then Biſhops of greateſt power (who might, by that <hi>Declaration,</hi> obtain li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to explain all things as they thought fit) favoured thoſe <hi>Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates</hi> of <hi>Arminianiſm,</hi> and muſt have been their Judges, if they had been complained of.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116869:4"/>2. That where (in <hi>Art.</hi> 16.) it is ſaid, <hi>Not every deadly ſin willingly committed after Baptiſm, is a ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> We may not dare to open the nature of <hi>deadly ſin;</hi> nor, to ſay, that <hi>all ſins are deadly,</hi> contrary to the Popiſh diſtinction of ſins into <hi>mortal</hi> and <hi>venial.</hi> Nor may we preſume to explain the next part of that <hi>Article, viz. After we have received the Holy Ghoſt, we may depart from grace given,</hi> &amp;c. which Clauſe, Biſhop <hi>Montacute,</hi> and (after him) others allege to prove <hi>falling from grace;</hi> and thereby pretend that this is the <hi>Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England, which is contrary not onely to <hi>Art.</hi> 17. but, to 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That, it being ſaid (<hi>Art.</hi> 20.) <hi>The Church hath power to decree Rites or Ceremonies, and Authority in Controverſies of Faith;</hi> we may not enquire what is meant by the <hi>Church,</hi> whether the Church <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick;</hi> or, of <hi>England:</hi> nor what the <hi>Church of England</hi> is: what <hi>Rites</hi> or <hi>Ceremonies</hi> it may ordain: or how far her <hi>Authority</hi> exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in <hi>Controverſies of Faith.</hi> And if ſhe do happen to ordain ought, <hi>contrary to Gods Word,</hi> or <hi>expound one place of Scripture repugnant to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother;</hi> or, to <hi>enforce</hi> any thing to <hi>be believed for neceſſity of ſalvation,</hi> that is <hi>beſide</hi> the Word; no man may queſtion it; but we muſt (if a Convocation once declare for it) <hi>aſſent</hi> and <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> unto it, in the <hi>Literal and Grammatical ſenſe of it;</hi> or, be <hi>deprived of all Eccleſiaſtical Promotions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. That, whereas the 34 <hi>Article,</hi> treateth of <hi>the Traditions of the Church,</hi> we muſt not curiouſly ſearch what is here meant by <hi>Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> and whether it be meant of the <hi>Traditions</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or of any other Church. But we muſt reſt in this General, That <hi>whoſoever, through his private judgement willingly and purpoſely doth openly break the Traditions and Ceremonies of the Church, which be not repugnant to the Word of God, and be ordained by common Authority, ought to be rebuked openly, as offending againſt the common Order of the Church, hurting the Authority of the Magiſtrate, and wounding the weak.</hi> Whereas, this Church hath no where ſet forth what ſhe meaneth by <hi>Traditions;</hi> whether diſtinct from <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> or the ſame with them: how a <hi>Tradition</hi> may be ſaid to be ordained; and, what is meant by <hi>common Authority.</hi> Yea, if power be given to the <hi>Biſhops and Clergy in Convocation,</hi> when and ſo often as they ſhall deſire it, to <hi>ordain</hi> any more <hi>Traditions,</hi> (which ſeems to be a ſtrange Expreſſion) and new <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> and, the Royal <hi>Aſſent</hi> paſs thereupon, all Miniſters muſt ſubſcribe thereunto, before they know what they be; yea, before they be ordained: after which, it will be too late to diſpute them, or to <hi>vary from them in the leaſt degree,</hi> upon any pretence whatſoever. It will be too late then, for any man to ſay, They are <hi>repugnant to the Word of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. That all, being by <hi>Art.</hi> 35. to admit both Books of <hi>Homilies</hi> to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116869:5"/>
                     <hi>contain a godly and wholeſome Doctrine neceſſary for theſe times;</hi> and therefore, to be <hi>read in Churches by the Miniſters diligently,</hi> men muſt <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> to <hi>falſe Doctrines,</hi> or aſſertions. Take inſtance in but one or two particulars, for brevities ſake.</p>
                  <p>Par. 2. <hi>Hom.</hi> 2. <hi>Of the place and time of Prayer,</hi> pag. 147. <hi>Plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of wives was by ſpecial Prerogative ſuffered to the Fathers of the Old Teſtament, not for ſatisfying their carnal and fleſhly luſts; but, to have many children, becauſe every one of them hoped, and begged oft-times of God in their Prayers, that that bleſſed ſeed which God promiſed ſhould come into the world to break the Serpents head, might come, and be born of his ſtock and kindred.</hi> As if all did not know, out of what <hi>Tribe</hi> Chriſt was to iſſue.</p>
                  <p>Par. 2. <hi>Hom.</hi> 2. of <hi>Alms,</hi> pag. 160. <hi>The ſame leſſon doth the Holy Ghoſt teach us in ſundry places of the Scripture, ſaying, Mercifulneſs and alms-giving, purgeth from all ſins, delivereth from death, and ſuffereth not the ſoul to come into darkneſs,</hi> For this, is alledged, <hi>Tob.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. Then there is added, <hi>The wiſe Preacher the ſon of Sirach, confirmeth the ſame, when he ſaith, That as water quencheth burningfire, even ſo mercy and alms reſiſteth, and reconcileth ſins.</hi> (Excellent ſenſe!) For this, <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 5. is quoted in the margent. But, it is, <hi>cap.</hi> 3.30. where the words in the New Tranſlation are, <hi>Alms maketh an atonement for ſins.</hi> Of which words, however a charitable conſtruction may be wyre-drawn: yet, thoſe expreſſions, (the <hi>ſame leſſon</hi> doth the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> teach us in ſundry places of the <hi>Scripture</hi>) evidently admit of theſe two groſs Errours, 1. That the Book of <hi>Tobit</hi> is to be taken for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Scripture.</hi> 2. That it was indited by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> The former of theſe is contrary to <hi>Art.</hi> 6. in which, only the <hi>Canonical</hi> Books there named, are owned for the Scripture of the <hi>Old Teſtament:</hi> And that of <hi>Tobit</hi> is there numbred among the <hi>Apoeryphals,</hi> which the <hi>Article</hi> ſaith (out of <hi>Hierom</hi>) the <hi>Church doth not apply to eſtabliſh Doctrine:</hi> yet, this Homily applies theſe Apocryphal paſſages to confirm the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Alms deeds.</hi> And as touching the <hi>Holy Ghoſts</hi> teaching of this, in thoſe places alledged out of <hi>Tobit,</hi> and <hi>Siracides,</hi> this is denyed by all, who receive not thoſe Books as <hi>Canonical.</hi> Take but one witneſs (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of many) King <hi>James,</hi> who, in his Book directed to his Eldeſt ſon, and called <hi>Baſilicon Doren,</hi> having ſpoken to him of reading of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, ſaith thus: <hi>As to the Apocrypha Books, I omit them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am no Papiſt: and indeed ſome of them are no way like the dite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Spirit of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. That, by the 37th <hi>Article</hi> (as it is ſtill printed, and may not be altered) where it is ſaid, <hi>The Queens Majeſty hath the chief power in the Realm of England,</hi> &amp;c. (meaning Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who is after named therein;) all Miniſters are bound to read thoſe very words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day: and may not ſay, <hi>The Kings Majeſty</hi> hath the chief power;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116869:5"/>for the <hi>Articles</hi> muſt be read, every word of them as they are printed, with the Kings Declaration before them: or, the Miniſter muſt be deprived, if he <hi>alter</hi> any word, or ſhall not take it in the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the very <hi>Letter</hi> of it. And if he keep not to all the very words of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi> who can ſwear that he did read them after his <hi>Induction,</hi> if put unto it?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. That by this means, we ſhall have no <hi>ſetled</hi> or <hi>fixed Doctrine of the Church of England</hi> at all; if ſo often as the <hi>Biſhops and Clergy</hi> in <hi>Convocation,</hi> ſhall obtain <hi>Licenſe to deliberate</hi> of all ſuch things as they ſhall think fit to explain, and ſhall obtain thereto the Royal <hi>Aſſent,</hi> they may put what ſenſe they pleaſe, upon the <hi>Doctrine eſtabliſhed;</hi> which, by the <hi>Declaration</hi> prefixed to the <hi>Articles,</hi> is promiſed to be, <hi>from time to time</hi> granted unto them.</p>
                  <p>If it be ſaid, <hi>There is an eaſie Cure for all this. The Declaration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the</hi> 39 <hi>Articles, was never confirmed by any Act of Parliament, nor is now in force: or, if it be, it is but the taking of that away, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Books to be printed without it: So, will the ſubſcribers to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles be at as much liberty as by the Act of</hi> 13 <hi>Eliz. was allowed them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this it is Anſwered, that this will ſignifie nothing, if Miniſters be ſtill tyed to <hi>ſubſcription.</hi> For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It hath been already declared, (yea, <hi>adjudged</hi>) that, by that Statute, there is no liberty for any man to <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> the Articles with any limitation, or explication; if any credit be given to Sir <hi>Edward Cook,</hi> who ſaith
<note n="*" place="margin">Inſtit. 4.47. p. 324. edit. 1658.</note>, that he hath <hi>heard</hi> Wray <hi>chief Juſtice in the Kings Bench,</hi> Paſch. 23 Eliz. (<hi>quoting</hi> Dier 23 Eliz. 377. lib. 6. fol. 69. Grenes Caſe, Smiths Caſe) <hi>report, that where one</hi> Smith <hi>ſubſcribed to the ſaid</hi> 39 Articles <hi>of Religion, with this addition</hi> (ſo far forth as the ſame were agreeable to the Word of God) <hi>that it was reſolved by him, and all the Judges of</hi> England, <hi>that this ſubſcription was not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute of</hi> 13 Eliz. <hi>Becauſe the Statute required an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſubſcription, and this ſubſcription made it conditional; and that this Act was made for avoiding diverſities of opinions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And, by this Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the party might by his own private opinion, take ſome of them to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Word of God: and by this means diverſities of opinions ſhould not be avoided, which was the ſcope of the Statute; and the very Act it ſelf made touching ſubſcription, hereby of none effect.</hi> Thus, He.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This ſhews a neceſſity of repealing that branch of the Act, ſo far as it concerneth <hi>ſubſcription,</hi> becauſe, 1. if we may not ſubſcribe with ſuch an addition <hi>(ſo far forth as the ſame Articles are agreeable to Gods Word)</hi> it muſt needs be granted, that the Compoſers of them are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be <hi>infallible;</hi> and their <hi>Articles,</hi> of equal Authority with Canonical Scripture: or elſe, that the Statute intended to tyrannize over the Conſciences of men; which is not to be imagined. 2. There is no more neceſſity for Miniſters to ſubſcribe thoſe Articles which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116869:6"/>that <hi>Act</hi> confirmes, then there is for others to ſubſcribe to all other Acts of Parliament which do concern them. If an Act once confirm and ratifie a thing, under a penalty, it will take place, and keep all in as much obedience, as if all the Subſcriptions in the world were made to it. It is not particular Subſcriptions, but publique Legiſlative Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that makes it a binding Law. 3. This Subſcription, is for the moſt part, required of men, while they be young, and have not time, or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity throughly to ponder and weigh all the Articles, in the balance of the Sanctuary, or in the ſcaies of the Laws; ſo that hereby they are caſt into a ſnare ere they be aware; and, by their own inconſiderate and raſh act, bound (as men are apt to make them believe, if they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, upon never ſo juſt grounds, begin to heſitate) to maintain every of thoſe Articles, although <hi>contrary to the Word of God:</hi> which is expreſly contrary to the very Letter of the 20th <hi>Article,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>It is not lawful to ordain any thing that is contrary to Gods Word written.</hi> And afterwards, <hi>As it ought not to decree any thing againſt the ſame</hi> (that is, the <hi>Word</hi>) <hi>ſo, beſide the ſame, ought it not to enforce any thing to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved for neceſſity of Salvation.</hi> But the Statute doth require belief of every one of theſe Articles, when it enjoyns not only <hi>ſubſcription,</hi> but an <hi>aſſent</hi> unto them, puniſhing all with <hi>Deprivation,</hi> that ſhall <hi>affirm,</hi> and <hi>maintain</hi> any Doctrine <hi>repugnant</hi> to them; which every man muſt do, if they be found contrariant to the Word; or, he muſt be falſe to God. 4. If <hi>ſubſcription</hi> to theſe, or any other Articles, be ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, How can any <hi>juſt liberty be granted to tender Conſciences;</hi> But that they muſt ſwallow all that is enjoyned, although beſide (yea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to) the Word, or be perſecuted and ruined? Thus much of the <hi>Doubtfulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Articles,</hi> and of the inconvenience and miſchief of <hi>ſubſcribing</hi> them. Which inconvenience and miſchief will be greater, if we ſhould be tyed to thoſe Articles alone (though never ſo ſound:) as ſhall now appear in the <hi>Defectiveneſs</hi> of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Articles</hi> are <hi>Defective:</hi> Becauſe</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſixth <hi>Article,</hi> ſpeaking of the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> ſaith, <hi>In the name of the holy Scripture, we do underſtand thoſe Canonical Books of the Old and New Teſtament, of whoſe Authority there was never any doubt in the Church.</hi> Nevertheleſs, albeit it enumerate the <hi>Canonical Books</hi> of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> (yea, and all the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> too) yet it nameth not any of the New Teſtament; but only concludeth thus; <hi>All the Books of the New Teſtament, as they are commonly received, we do receive and account Canonical.</hi> Now, it being not unknown, that there hath been <hi>doubts in the Church,</hi> of ſome of them; inſomuch as the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of St. <hi>James,</hi> the ſecond Epiſtle of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſeveral other books and paſſages in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> have been not only doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but refuſed; the Article is <hi>defective</hi> in the not enumerating all the Books of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116869:6"/>2. There are no <hi>Articles</hi> for diſcovering and condemning ſundry points of <hi>Popery</hi> in Doctrine, which (being firſt the Tenets of <hi>Arminius,</hi> the firſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Writer that was not a profeſſed <hi>Lutheran,</hi> that ever openly maintained them) are too commonly ſuckt in, and cryed up by ſome, as the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which, ſince the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, never own'd them; but are all maintained by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and generally by all <hi>Franciſcans</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> but confuted by all appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Writers of the Proteſtant Reformed party, that have written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others of that crew: as likewiſe by the learned <hi>Whitgift, Whitaker, Junius, Zanchius, Pareus, Chamier,</hi> Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> and many others. The learned King <hi>James</hi> alſo took ſo much notice of, and diſtaſte at thoſe <hi>Arminian-Popiſh</hi> Opinions touching <hi>Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion abuſed, univerſal Redemption, univerſal Grace, the manner of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and falling from grace;</hi> that his Majeſty was the chief procurer and promoter of the late <hi>Synode</hi> of <hi>Dort,</hi> to which he ſent Biſhop <hi>Carl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Davenant,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hall,</hi> (afterwards, Biſhops) Dr. <hi>Goad,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Balcanqual,</hi> to aſſiſt in that Synode; whoſe judgements touching all thoſe points, were given in to the ſaid <hi>Council,</hi> ſubſcribed with their hands, and afterwards printed and publiſhed. Agreeable whereunto, in the main, hath the late <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their judgements in the <hi>Confeſſion of Faith</hi> (afterwards ratified by both Houſes of the late Long <hi>Parliment:</hi>) for which reaſon is that <hi>Aſſembly</hi> ſo much ſlighted, reviled, and oppoſed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Thoſe Articles contain nothing of the <hi>Creation,</hi> of <hi>Providence, Fall</hi> of man, of <hi>Sin,</hi> of the <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of ſin, of Gods <hi>Covenants, Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Calling, Adoption, Sanctification, Faith, Repentance, Perſeverance,</hi> of the <hi>Law of God, Chriſtian liberty</hi> and <hi>Liberty of conſcience, Religious Worſhip,</hi> of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> or <hi>Lords day,</hi> of <hi>Marriage</hi> and <hi>Divorce,</hi> the <hi>Communion of Saints, Church-government and Diſcipline,</hi> of the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> or of the <hi>laſt Judgement;</hi> all which the <hi>Scripture</hi> teacheth, and that, as <hi>neceſſary;</hi> as appears by the comprizing moſt of them in the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> and therefore neceſſary to be explained and held forth unto all, as the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of this <hi>Church;</hi> eſpecially conſidering the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and Controverſies about many of them. Upon this reaſon it was, that the late Aſſembly of Divines have taken ſo much pains to compoſe ſeveral <hi>Articles</hi> (which they call Chapters;) wherein both thoſe of the 39 <hi>Articles</hi> which are held to be indeed fit to be retained, are more fully cleared and explained; and the reſt, added, with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent proofs of <hi>Scripture,</hi> to make it manifeſt that they are all evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded upon the Word of God. But, all proofs are wanting in the 39 <hi>Articles:</hi> no text of Scripture being produced to make cut any one of them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116869:7"/>
               <head>II. <hi>Of</hi> WORSHIP.</head>
               <p>THe Form of <hi>Publick Worſhip</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> (except <hi>Preaching</hi>) is ſet down in the <hi>Liturgy</hi> or Book of Common-Prayer, eſtabliſhed by Law, in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. intituled, <hi>An Act for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of Common-Prayer and Service in the Church, and the Adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> This Act repealeth another, made in 1 <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. which had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed a former Statute made in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of Common-Prayer,</hi> &amp;c. and re-eſtabliſhed that <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> which the ſaid laſt mentioned Act of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. had ratified and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. But yet the Act of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> which authorizeth and enjoyneth the uſe of that Book of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. doth it, with allowance of one <hi>alteration or addition of certain Leſſons to be uſed on every Sunday in the year, and the form of the Letany altered and corrected, and two ſentences onely added in the delivery of the Sacrament to the Communicants:</hi> but, <hi>none other, or otherwiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, it is here to be obſerved, that in the Act of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. for confirming that Book, it is ſaid, that, <hi>The Kings moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, with th' aſſent of the Lords and Commons in that Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and by the Authority of the ſame, had cauſed the aforeſaid Order of common ſervice, intituled,</hi> The Book of Common-Prayer, <hi>to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and godly peruſed, explained, and made fully perfect, and by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Authority annexed and enjoyned it ſo explained and perfected, to that preſent Statute.</hi> So that the ſame was enrolled together with the Act it ſelf. Which being repealed by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the Original Book was taken off from the Parliament-Roll, and ſo loſt.</p>
               <p>But, in the Act of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. there is no mention at all of joyning the Book then revived and re-confirmed, to the ſaid Act: nor doth it appear that ever it was again enrolled, whereby, by having recourſe to any Record or Parliament-Roll, it may be proved, that that Book of Common-Prayer, printed in the year 1559. (the firſt of Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>een <hi>Eliz.</hi>) is confirmed by Law, or that any man is bound to uſe it as the onely form now eſtabliſhed by Parliament; or, to be puniſhed for not uſing it at all.</p>
               <p>And albeit the <hi>Act</hi> of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quere</hi> therefore whether he that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſeth them not; or uſeth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be puniſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</note> taketh notice of ſome <hi>alterations</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned, to be made in the Book then ratified, yet it doth not name, nor expreſs what thoſe <hi>alterations</hi> were. So that all men are leſt in a blind touching the ſame, if put to prove that thoſe alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons now found in the printed Common-Prayer Books, are the very ſame, which the laſt mentioned Act intended to allow and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:116869:7"/>
               <p>Howbeit, that we may go ſo far as we can herein, take notice that by-comparing the Book printed in 5, 6, <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. with that which was prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> the alterations therein found (which are onely hinted in the Stat. of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2.) are theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. As touching <hi>Proper Leſſons.</hi> The <hi>Kalendar</hi> of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed no <hi>Proper Leſſons</hi> for <hi>Sundays</hi> (except for <hi>Eaſter-day, Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunday,</hi> and <hi>Trinity Sunday</hi>) but onely for <hi>Holy-Days.</hi> The <hi>Leſſons</hi> for all other Sundays, were onely ſet down in the <hi>Kalendar</hi> in ordinary courſe of reading the reſt of the Bible, upon that, and other days of the week, in a continued way of reading all. But, the Book, in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> in the Kalendar of <hi>Proper Leſſons,</hi> hath it thus; <hi>Proper Leſſons to be read, for the firſt Leſſons both at morning Prayer and evening Prayer on the Sundays, throughout the year; and, for ſome alſo, the ſecond Leſſons.</hi> Then, it after adds, <hi>Leſſons proper for Holy Days.</hi> All which <hi>proper Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> were appointed in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> to take place of all Chapters which in ordinary courſe of reading, according to the day of each moneth, had been before ordered in the Kalendar to be read, without reſpect to either <hi>Sunday</hi> or Holy-Day, but onely to the day of the moneth in courſe. What <hi>alterations</hi> have been made either in that Book printed <hi>An.</hi> 1559. 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> of other <hi>proper Leſſons,</hi> not warranted by the Act of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. (namely, of ſuch as were before appointed for <hi>Holy-days,</hi> &amp;c.) or that have been made ſince, ſhall be afterwards ſhewed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As touching the <hi>Letany,</hi> there is no material alteration in that, ſave onely this; that whereas both the Books of 2 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. ran thus: <hi>From all ſedition and privy conſpiracy, from the tyranny of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>and all his deteſtable Enormities, from all falſe Doctrine and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> &amp;c. thoſe words touching the <hi>tyranny of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>and all his deteſtable Enormities,</hi> are leſt out in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. and ever ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> the words uſed at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of the <hi>bread, and wine,</hi> ran thus: <hi>Take and eat this in remembrance that Chriſt dyed for thee, and feed on him in thine heart by faith with thanksgiving:</hi> but in the Book of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and in all ſince, the words are theſe: <hi>The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt which was given for thee, preſerve thy body and ſoul unto everlaſting life; take and eat this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that Chriſt dyed for thee, and feed on him in thine heart by faith with thanksgiving.</hi> The words at giving the Cup, in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. were theſe: <hi>Drink this in remembrance Chriſts blood was ſhed for thee, and be thankful.</hi> But in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and ſince, the words are, <hi>The Blood of our Jeſus Chriſt which was ſhed for thee, preſerve thy Body and Soul into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life; drink this, in remembrance Chriſts Blood was ſhed for thee, and be thankful.</hi> Now, it is to be noted, that, whereas onely the two former Clauſes, which run in the forms of Prayers, were in the Book of 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and the two latter Clauſes onely, are in the Book of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116869:8"/>5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. as here above ſhewed, that Book of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> takes in, and joyns them both together. If theſe be not the <hi>alterations</hi> to which the Act of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> referreth, it will be very difficult (if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible) to find what they were.</p>
               <p>Now having thus prepared the way to ſpeak to the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> in <hi>Worſhip,</hi> it is deſired that all Readers of this Piece, will take notice, that there was lately printed, in one ſheet of Paper, <hi>ſome of the Differences and alterations in the preſent Common-Prayer-Book from that which was eſtabliſhed by Law</hi> in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> (or, at leaſt ſuppoſed ſo to be) which is but a <hi>Specimen,</hi> or ſhort hint of what is here intended to be ſet forth more largely and fully: and that, in the ſame Order and Method which is there propounded; (none of thoſe printed Papers being now left) it is thought fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print and inſert that ſheet (with ſome few Reviſals) in this larger Tract, which ſhall now follow in the next place. And then after that, we ſhall add what ſhall be neceſſary for making out more fully the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of reforming the whole <hi>Liturgy;</hi> not by way of <hi>reducing,</hi> ſo much as of <hi>new moulding</hi> the whole.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:116869:8"/>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="tract">
                           <head>Some of the DIFFERENCES and ALTERATIONS In the preſent Common-Prayer-Book, FROM The Book eſtabliſhed by Law, in <hi>quinto &amp; ſexto, Edw.</hi> 6. and 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <div type="part">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>The</hi> KALENDAR.</head>
                              <p>THere are ſundry Saints days (although in black Letters) not found in the Books of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. or 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> to the number of 50. and moe. Which however it may ſeem a ſmall matter, yet Time may turn them into <hi>Red</hi> Letters, and ſo claim obſervance of them. For Dr. <hi>Couſens</hi> in his <hi>Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar</hi> (which he calls the <hi>Kalendar of the Church</hi>) in his Book of <hi>Devotion,</hi> hath put one of them already, <hi>viz.</hi> St. <hi>Barnabies</hi> Day, into <hi>Red.</hi> But, however the <hi>Epiſtle and Goſpel</hi> for that day, and for <hi>the Converſion of St. Paul,</hi> be extant in the Service-Book; (and, in the <hi>Liturgy</hi> printed for <hi>Scotland,</hi> An. 1637. both theſe are put into <hi>Red,</hi> and enjoyned to be obſerved) yet in 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. thoſe days were expun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of the Catalogue of Holy Days.</p>
                              <p>On <hi>Aug.</hi> 7. <hi>The Name of Jeſus</hi> is put in for an old <hi>Holy-day;</hi> which, however uſed in times of Popery, (but, under a more gentle Title
<note n="a" place="margin">Feſt. Jeſu.</note>) yet even in 2. as well as in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> it was expelled. Howbeit, Dr. <hi>Couſens,</hi> in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Devotions,</hi> hath already ſet down proper Leſſons
<pb facs="tcp:116869:9"/>for that <hi>day, viz. Mat.</hi> 1. and <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. which ſhews how deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſome are to keep an Holy-day to a Name.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div type="part">
                              <head>The Order for Proper Leſſons.</head>
                              <p>On <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> the <hi>firſt Leſſon</hi> at <hi>Even. Prayer,</hi> was <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. now, that is thruſt out, and <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 1. crept into the room. And if we look into the <hi>Leſſons</hi> for <hi>Holy-days,</hi> we ſhall find many Chapters of the <hi>Canonical</hi> Scripture laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and <hi>Apochyphal</hi> Chapters ordered to be read. See ſome inſtances in the Margent, at the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<note n="c" place="margin">Old Kalendar. The New.
<table>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Jan.</hi> 25. Gen. 46.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 5.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Jan.</hi> 25. Gen. 47.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 6.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. Exod. 12.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 9.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. Exod 13.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 12.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Feb.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>. Numb. 33.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 19.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Jun.</hi> 29. Job 31.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 15.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Jun.</hi> 29. Job 32.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus</hi> 19.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Jul.</hi> 25. Eccleſ. 10.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 21.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Jul.</hi> 25. Eccleſ 11.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 23.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. Ezek 3.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 25.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. Ezek 6.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 29.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Sep.</hi> 21. Mic. 7.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus</hi> 35.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Sep.</hi> 21. Naum. 1.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus</hi> 38.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Sept.</hi> 29. Zach 7.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 39.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Sept.</hi> 29. Zach 8.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 44.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Octob.</hi> 18. Judg. 14.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 
                                             <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                                <desc>•</desc>
                                             </gap>1.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                       <row>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Dec.</hi> 28. Iſa. 60.</cell>
                                          <cell>
                                             <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 1.</cell>
                                       </row>
                                    </table>
                                 </note>.</p>
                              <p>There are ſundry other Leſſons altered, which I here omit. It is true, the <hi>Stat.</hi> of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> alloweth <hi>one alteration or addition of certain Leſſons to be uſed on every Sunday in the year:</hi> but, after mention of ſome <hi>by name,</hi> it addeth, <hi>And none other, or otherwiſe.</hi> Alſo in the preſent <hi>Kalendars,</hi> there are four Chapters of <hi>Joſhua</hi> left out, that were in the <hi>Kalendars</hi> of 5. and 6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. And, on <hi>Octob.</hi> 13. <hi>Judith</hi> 15.16. are appointed now to be read; which was not ſo in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves conſideration, ſeeing ſo many <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Chapters of uſe, are not at all appointed to be read in publick.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div type="part">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>The</hi> RUBRICKS.</head>
                              <p>The firſt Page of the preſent Books, appoint Miniſters to uſe ſuch Ornaments as were of uſe in 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. not decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what they be.
<note place="margin">The Book of 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned onely a <hi>ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>lis</hi> in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches and Chappels. See laſt page of that Book, where are <hi>notes for explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> So alſo, in <hi>Rubr.</hi> before <hi>Morn. Prayer.</hi> 5 6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.</note> The Book eſtabliſhed in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. names a <hi>Surplice onely.</hi> The Book of <hi>Canons, Can.</hi> 58. enjoyneth other Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Hereby ſome <hi>Miniſters</hi> muſt break that <hi>Canon,</hi> or the preſent <hi>Rubrick,</hi> which the 14th <hi>Canon</hi> requireth all to obſerve. So that the 14th <hi>Canon</hi> and the 58th contradict each other. And nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:116869:9"/>thoſe <hi>Canons,</hi> nor that Rubrick, nor this Book, are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law.</p>
                              <p>After the <hi>Communion,</hi> there are in all Service-Books of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. ſeven <hi>Rubricks.</hi> Which number remaineth; but, the Third is divided into two, and the fourth wholly loſt. In which fourth, the Compilers had ſolidly and excellently declared in what ſenſe they intended <hi>Kneeling at the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> The loſs whereof hath occaſioned much ſtumbling and offence; yea, much trouble and perſecution. That <hi>Rubrick</hi> was this.</p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Although no Order can be ſo perfectly deviſed, but it may be of ſome, either for their Ignorance and Infirmity, or elſe of Malice and Obſtinacy, miſconstrued, depraved, or interpreted in a wrong part; yet becauſe brotherly Charity willeth that, ſo much as conveniently may be, Offences ſhould be taken away; therefore we willing to do the ſame. Whereas it is Ordained in the Book of Common-Prayer, in the Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, that the Communicants, kneeling, ſhould receive the Holy Communion; which thing being well meant for a ſignification of the humble and grateful acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of the benefits of Chriſt, given unto the Worthy Receiver, and to avoid the profanation and diſorder which about the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion might elſe enſue. Leſt yet the ſame kneeling might be thought or taken otherwiſe, we do declare, that it is not meant thereby, that any Adoration is done, or ought to be done, either unto the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Bread &amp; Wine there bodily received, nor unto any real and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Preſence there being of Chriſts natural fleſh and blood. For, as concerning the Sacramental Bread and Wine, they remain ſtill in their very natural Subſtances, and therefore may not be adored: for, that were Idolatry to be abhorred of all faithful Chriſtians. And, as concerning the natural Body and Bloud of our Saviour Chriſt, they are in Heaven, and not here: for it is contrary to the truth of Chriſts true natural Body to be in moe places than one, at one time.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                           <div type="part">
                              <head>The Body of the Book it ſelf.</head>
                              <p>There is a whole Prayer now left out, at the end of the
<pb facs="tcp:116869:10"/>
                                 <hi>Letany,</hi> which was extant in the Books of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. to be uſed in times of Dearth or Famine: which was this:</p>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>O God merciful Father, which in the time of</hi> Heliſeus <hi>the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, didſt ſuddenly turn in</hi> Samaria, <hi>great ſcarcity and dearth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to plenty and cheapneſs, and extream famine into abundance of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual; have pity upon us that now be puniſhed for our ſins with like adverſity. Encreaſe the fruits of the Earth by thy heavenly benedi, ction; and grant that we receiving thy bountifvl liberality, may uſe the ſame to thy glory. our comfort, and relief of our needy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, through Jeſu Christ our Lord, Amen.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Moreover, there are ſundry Prayers (ſome before ſome in King <hi>James</hi> his time) put into the preſent Leiturgy; as alſo ſome things into the Catechiſm, which are not confirmed by Parliament. Which Additions (although uſeful) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not legally ratified, hath imboldened ſome to make al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations at their pleaſure. For inſtance, The Prayer for the <hi>Queen</hi> and Royal <hi>Family,</hi> before the year 1627. began thus; <hi>Almighty God which haſt promiſed to be a Father of thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and of their ſeed:</hi> but now, thus; <hi>Almighty God the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of all goodneſs.</hi> Which change was a great Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and may ſeem to imply an excluſion of the Royal Stem out of the number of Gods <hi>Elect.</hi> This alteration was firſt made in the Books appointed to be uſed, about that time, at publick Faſts; and thence, was ſtollen into the Book of Common-Prayer. Of which, no reaſon can be diſcovered, unleſs this; that the word <hi>Elect,</hi> diſtaſted the favourers of Popiſh <hi>Arminianiſm.</hi>
                              </p>
                              <p>Likewiſe the reading Pſalms, now thruſt into the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Books, (pretended to be eſtabliſhed by Law) were no part thereof in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> or in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> For neither of the Books then printed in <hi>Folio,</hi> for publick uſe in Churches, had the Pſalms in them; but only a direction what Pſalms ſhould every day be read; which were accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly read out of the Bibles then uſed in Churches. It is therefore, very hard, and unreaſonable, to continue that Tranſlation; and, to enjoyn, and tye men to read out thoſe abuſed Pſalms, as now they ſtand in that Book. And it is a great wrong to the people: that Verſion being very defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb facs="tcp:116869:10"/>and corrupt. Take ſome inſtances wherein that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from the Kings laſt authorized Tranſlation now only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be read in Churches; as alſo, from the Original it ſelf.</p>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Pſal. 28.9. <hi>The Lord is my ſtrength.</hi> In the new, thus,
<note place="margin">Old Tranſt.</note> 
                                    <hi>The Lord is their ſtrength,</hi> ver. 8.</item>
                                 <item>37.38. <hi>Keep innocency, and take heed to the thing that is right.</hi> In the new, <hi>Mark the perfect man, and behold the juſt,</hi> ver. 37.</item>
                                 <item>58.8. <hi>So let indignation vex them as a thing that is raw.</hi> In the new, <hi>He taketh them away as with a whirlewind, both living and in his wrath,</hi> ver. 9.</item>
                                 <item>68.6. <hi>Maketh men to be of one mind in an houſe.</hi> In the new, <hi>Setteth the ſolitary in families.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>105.28. <hi>They were not obedient.</hi> In the new, <hi>They rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not againſt his word</hi>
                                    <note n="*" place="margin">
                                       <hi>Let which of thoſe by</hi> Fuller <hi>or Dr.</hi> Pride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aux <hi>be thought the better; yet, while they both ſtand, they cauſe ſcandal.</hi>
                                    </note>.</item>
                                 <item>107.40. <hi>Though he ſuffer them to be evil intreated.</hi> In the new, <hi>He poureth contempt upon Princes.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>125.3. <hi>The rod of the wicked cometh not.</hi> In the new, <hi>the rod of the wicked reſteth not upon the lot of the righteous.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                              <p>In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. there are three whole Verſes, which are not in the Original, nor in the reviſed Tranſlation, nor in the Greek 72. but only in the Popiſh vulgar Bibles. To excuſe it by ſaying, All thoſe Verſes are found together in <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. is a fig-leaf. For, the Apoſtle never meant to produce all thoſe words as taken out of one place; but only to collect out of ſeveral Texts of the Old Teſtament, ſundry teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to prove <hi>all men to be ſinners.</hi> Accordingly, he took three Verſes out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. one out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140. another out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. another out of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. All which, the Old Tranſlators unadviſedly thruſt into the 14. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> as parts of that one Scripture.</p>
                              <p>I forbear to mention other <hi>Pſalms,</hi> wherein, ſometimes words, ſometimes whole verſes are left out; and, much of the reſt is very improperly and impertinently tranſlated: which in the Leiturgy provided for <hi>Scotland,</hi> was redreſſed; yet the Book (for ſundry other defects, impertinencies, and
<pb facs="tcp:116869:11"/>redundances) was refuſed: This makes ſport for Papiſts and Atheiſts, to find how much our Tranſlations publickly uſed, do enterfere, and jar; and how corrupt ſome of them be.</p>
                              <p>Thus of the differences between the old Common-prayer-books confirmed by Law, and the preſent Common-prayer-books ſo much magnified and adored, not only by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort, but by too many of thoſe who pretend to learning and skill in the Publike <hi>Offices</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but abuſe the people; yea, Magiſtracy, and God himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. For, ſtill the <hi>Preface</hi> of the Book runs thus: <hi>That nothing is enjoyned to be read, but that which is the pure word of God, or that which is evidently grounded thereupon:</hi> which (as our bold Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have ordered the matter) is falſe; and a meer cheat put upon the people of God.</p>
                              <p>Having thus given a taſte of the Differences between the Old and New Books, I hold it needful to ſhew how unſafe it might be hereupon to conclude no more but this: <hi>Then let the preſent Book of Common-prayer be compared with the old that was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, and be reformed by it.</hi> For, even in the Book that was eſtabliſhed by Parliament, there are ſundry incongru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and uncomely expreſſions, unwarrantable paſſages, and, ſome groſs miſtakes of the Scripture it ſelf; eſpecially in the Tranſlations of the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> and <hi>Goſpels.</hi> Which Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation uſed in the Book of Common-prayer, is as antient as the 35. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. (and uſed firſt in private <hi>Primmars,</hi> being tranſlated out of the Maſs books and other Offices of the Romiſh Church) for want of a better Tranſlation in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth. For Example,
<list>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>ſp.</hi>
                                       <note place="margin">The old Tranſlation.</note> on 2 Sund. after <hi>Epiph. When men be drunk.</hi> But, in the new, <hi>When men have well drunk.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
                                       <note place="margin">
                                          <hi>Indeed Dr.</hi> Prideaux <hi>ſaith, all theſe are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the Kings New Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the Bible. But what is this to the Service-book, in which theſe corrupt paſſages are ſtill printed, and preſſed to be read in Divine Service?</hi>
                                       </note> on 4 Sund. in <hi>Lent. Mount Sinai is Agar in Arabia, and horder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon the City which is now called Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> a groſs miſtake both of Scripture, and Topography. The new Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therefore renders it thus: <hi>This Hagar
<pb facs="tcp:116869:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>is mount Sinai in Arabia, and anſwereth to Hieruſalem which now is.</hi> He ſaith not, <hi>Mount Sinai is Agar;</hi> for, that is not ſo. But, <hi>Hagar is mount Sinai:</hi> that is, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation or figure of it. Nor doth the Apoſtle ſay, that <hi>mount Sinai in Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia bordered upon Hieruſalem.</hi> For, that is falſe; <hi>Arabia</hi> being many hundred miles diſtant from <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> And the <hi>Mount</hi> whereof St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, was a type of it, not <hi>bordering</hi> on it.</item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Epiſt.</hi> on <hi>Palm</hi>-Sunday. <hi>He was found in his apparel as a man.</hi> In the new, <hi>He was found in faſhion as a man.</hi> The word is <gap reason="foreign">
                                          <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                       </gap> which imports, not appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, but the form, or figure, which inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the real ſubſtance and true nature of the thing whereof it is a form.</item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Epiſt.</hi> on 16 Sun. after <hi>Trin. Which is Father of all that is called father in heaven and in earth.</hi> Then, the Father, muſt needs be Father to himſelf. The new Tranſlation, therefore renders it, <hi>Of whom the whole family of heaven and earth is named.</hi> So the Original, <gap reason="foreign">
                                          <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                       </gap>.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </p>
                              <p>Much more might be added, not only againſt the preſent uneſtabliſhed Leiturgy, but againſt that which was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. But this ſhall ſuffice. For my intention neither is, nor ever was, to deſtroy, or caſt off all Forms: but only to ſhew ſome grounds of exception againſt this. And ſeeing this is ſo much cried up, that the moſt, place all their Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Religion in it, and come little ſhort of the Iſraelites in abuſing of the <hi>brazen Serpent,</hi> which by Gods own com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, was erected in the Wilderneſs; Authority may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider whether it be not honourable, ſafe, and neceſſary to deal with both Books, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did with that Idolized <hi>Serpent;</hi> and carefully to provide a better in the room; as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116869:12"/>that good King did, in reforming the whole Publick Service of God: there being now far better means, and fairer oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of ſo doing, than in the times of compiling the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Leiturgy by thoſe Reverend and Renowned Biſhops and Matyrs that did compoſe it.</p>
                           </div>
                           <epigraph>
                              <bibl>
                                 <hi>ROM. 10.22.</hi>
                              </bibl>
                              <q>Happy is he that condemneth not himſelf in that thing which he alloweth.</q>
                           </epigraph>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Having reprinted the foregoing Sheet, we muſt now go on, in the ſame Order and Method (as was before promiſed) to obſerve ſome more incongruous and unworthy paſſages (all which call for a New Form of <hi>Liturgy</hi>) in the reſt of the <hi>Kalendar, Rubricks,</hi> and <hi>Body</hi> of the Book it ſelf.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I. <hi>In the</hi> KALENDAR.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Kalendar</hi> is either that which appoints <hi>Proper</hi> Leſſons for <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days</hi> and <hi>Holy-days</hi> (to ſpeak in the <hi>Common-prayer-book</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) or that which in each Month ſheweth what Chapters are to be daily read on week-days, according to the days of the month; and is prefixed, in all Editions, to the Book it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Proper Leſſons</hi> appointed for <hi>Holy-days.</hi> The Kalendar of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. omitteth proper Leſſons for the <hi>Converſion of Paul,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was then no Holy-day, but abrogated by the Act of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. ca. 3. Therefore in the Common <hi>Kalendar</hi> then eſtabliſhed, the firſt Leſſons for that day (being <hi>Jan.</hi> 25.) as being a Common-day of the Week, were <hi>Gen.</hi> 46. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. But in the Book of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> theſe two Chapters are laid by, and <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 5, and 6. put in the room. This (however toucht upon in the printed Sheet) is here again taken notice of, to ſhew by this (among other arguments) that the Book then printed was not confirmed by 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. becauſe that Act admits of no <hi>alterations</hi> of Leſſons on <hi>Holy-days,</hi> or other days, ſave only on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116869:12"/>
                     <hi>Sundays.</hi> Yet is this alſo thruſt into the New Scotiſh <hi>Leiturgy,</hi> and that day, made an <hi>Holy-day</hi> again.</p>
                  <p>And whereas in all the proper Leſſons for <hi>Holy-days</hi> in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. only <hi>All Saints</hi> day, had, for thoſe Leſſons, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 3, and 5. and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Holy-day</hi> Leſſons were Leſſons out of the <hi>Canonical Books;</hi> the <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar</hi> of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> hath appointed 20. more <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Chapters for <hi>Holy-days,</hi> and thruſt out ſo many Canonical Chapters, that by the <hi>Kalendar</hi> of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. were appointed for thoſe very days; as for inſtance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label"> </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Kalendar</hi> 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Kal.</hi> of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On the <hi>Purification.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet, on <hi>Feb.</hi> 1 (which is the Day) <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 9. <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 12.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On St. <hi>Mathias.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet, on <hi>Feb.</hi> 25. (which is the Day) <hi>Numb.</hi> 33. <hi>Numb.</hi> 34.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 19. <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 3.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On the <hi>Annunciat.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet, on <hi>Mar.</hi> 25. (which is the day) <hi>Joſh.</hi> 21. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 2. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 3.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On St. <hi>Mark.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet, on <hi>Apr.</hi> 25 (which is the day) 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ecclus</hi> 4. <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 5.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On St. <hi>Barnaby.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: 'tis no holy-day. Yet on <hi>June</hi> 11. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 3. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 4.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet on <hi>Jun.</hi> 29. (which is the day) <hi>Job.</hi> 31. <hi>Job.</hi> 32.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Eccl.</hi> 15. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 19.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On St. <hi>James.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet on <hi>July</hi> 25. (which is the day) <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Eccl.</hi> 21. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 23.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On St. <hi>Barthol.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet, on <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. (which is the day) <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Eccl.</hi> 25. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 29.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On St. <hi>Matthew.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet, on <hi>Sept.</hi> 21. (which is the day) <hi>Mic.</hi> 7. <hi>Naum</hi> 1.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Eccl.</hi> 35. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 38.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>On St. <hi>Mich.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>None: yet, on <hi>Sept.</hi> 29. (which is the day) <hi>Zech.</hi> 7. <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Eccl.</hi> 39. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 44.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Can we think there could ever have been ſo much boldneſs in thoſe that printed the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> to make ſo many alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, in that very year wherein the Act of <hi>Eliz.</hi> paſſed for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. (which admits not of one of them:) if that Book (which hath been followed ever ſince) printed in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> were the very Book then re-eſtabliſhed? And is not every Miniſter which readeth thoſe <hi>Apocryphals</hi> on the days aforeſaid, puniſhable (if he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth therein) by the <hi>Act</hi> of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2?</p>
                  <p>And here, let it be noted, that albeit there be ſundry whole <hi>Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116869:13"/>Books left out, and no leſs then 188. Chapters of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not read at all: yet, of the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> which contains but 173 Chapters, there are read 121 Chapters, by the <hi>Kalendar</hi> of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. as well as the <hi>Kalendars</hi> of later date. Whereas St. <hi>Hierom</hi> in his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for reading the Scriptures in private, by an holy woman, gives warning, <hi>Caveat omnia Apocrypha.</hi> Let her beware of all the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrypha.</hi> Which is not unlike to that of King <hi>James,</hi> to his <hi>Son,</hi> who, by ſaying, <hi>(I omit them, becauſe I am no Papiſt)</hi> declares plainly, that ſuch husks were firſt caſt before the Church by <hi>Popery,</hi> and is fit food for none but doting Papiſts. No more is that <hi>Kalendar,</hi> of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. from <hi>Octob.</hi> 5. to <hi>Novemb.</hi> 28. wherein very few <hi>Canonical</hi> Chapters are appointed to be read.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall now offer one Obſervation out of the late compiled <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> for <hi>Scotland,</hi> which is this; that (however ſo many <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Chapters ſtill ſtand in our <hi>Liturgies:</hi>) in all the <hi>Kalendar</hi> for <hi>Scotland,</hi> there are but 12. <hi>Apocryphals</hi> to be read in their Churches (which yet, they would not endure:) this ſhews plainly, that our great zealous Maſters who gave order for the Compoſing of that Book, had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what upon their Conſciences that rounded them in the ear againſt the continuing ſo many <hi>Apocryphals</hi> in ours: eſpecially conſidering that ſome of them, have been reputed but <hi>Fables</hi> (as namely the Book of <hi>Judith,</hi> the Hiſtory of <hi>Suſanna,</hi> &amp;c.) acted firſt in <hi>Interludes</hi> or <hi>Plays.</hi> And ſome of the Chapters contain meer deluſions and lyes: yet even thoſe very Chapters are appointed to be read in our Churches.</p>
                  <p>To make this laſt out, take notice of ſomewhat obſerved before, out of the ſecond <hi>Homily</hi> of <hi>Alms-deeds,</hi> which quoteth <hi>Tobit</hi> 4. and <hi>Ecclu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 5. (both being appointed to be read, the one <hi>Octob.</hi> 6. the other <hi>Octob.</hi> 30.) which I here paſs over. In <hi>Tobit</hi> 3. (appointed by the Kalendar of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. to be read <hi>Octob.</hi> 6.) where mention is made, ver. 8. that <hi>Sarah the daughter of Raguel</hi> had been <hi>marryed to ſeven husbands, whom Aſmodeus the evil ſpirit, had killed, before they had lien with her.</hi> (a likely matter!) Yet was ſhe <hi>reproached</hi> by her own <hi>Fathers maids,</hi> that <hi>ſhe had ſtrangled them all.</hi> In <hi>Tobit</hi> 3. (ordered to be read <hi>Octob.</hi> 9.) ver. 9. it is ſaid, <hi>Alms doth deliver from death, and ſhall purge away all ſin.</hi> What need then the bloud of Chriſt? And in ver. 15. one <hi>Raphael</hi> telleth <hi>Tobit,</hi> thus: <hi>I am Raphael one of the ſeven holy Angels, which preſent the prayers of the Saints, and which go in and out before the glory of the holy One.</hi> Whereas none but the <hi>Angel of the Covenant,</hi> now at the right hand of God to make interceſſion for the Saints, do preſent their prayers, <hi>Revel.</hi> 8.3. This <hi>Raphael</hi> was far from being one of the <hi>Angels that go in and out before the glory of the holy one;</hi> for he was a lying either man, or ſpirit. This was he that was hired by <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bias,</hi> ſon to <hi>Tobit,</hi> to ſhew him the way to <hi>Rages;</hi> and being asked by <hi>Tobit</hi> himſelf, of what Tribe he was, anſwered, <hi>I am Azarias the ſon of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116869:13"/>Ananias the great, and of thy brethren,</hi> Tob. 5.12. Now, you find him in two tales to the ſame man: in one of which he muſt needs lye. They that deſire to read more of his pranks, may read that Book of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit:</hi> and particularly, Chap. 6. where he taught <hi>Tobias</hi> how to chaſe away the Devil, by taking the <hi>heart,</hi> the <hi>liver</hi> and <hi>gall</hi> of a <hi>fiſh,</hi> and thereof to make a <hi>ſmoak,</hi> which when the Devil (who was ſaid to be in love with <hi>Sarah</hi> before named, and therefore in the Marriage-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, had killed thoſe ſeven husbands, before mentioned, who had marryed her) ſhould <hi>ſmell,</hi> he ſhould <hi>flee away, and never come again any more.</hi> And are not theſe gallant Chapters to be read in Churches? yet our Kalendar appointeth them to be read, <hi>viz. Tob.</hi> 5. and 6. on <hi>Octob.</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>So likewiſe <hi>Judith,</hi> cap. 9. (appointed to be read, <hi>Octob.</hi> 16.) tells a ſtory of a prayer which her ſelf made to God, (when ſhe had it in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to cut off <hi>Holofernes</hi> head:) in which prayer ſhe takes notice of father <hi>Simeon</hi> (who with <hi>Levi</hi> ſlew the <hi>Shechemites,</hi> for deflouring their ſiſters; <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.) and tells God, concerning the <hi>Shechemites,</hi> ver. 4. <hi>Thou haſt given their wives for a prey, and their daughters to be captives, and all their ſpoils to be divided among thy dear children, which were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with thy zeal, and abhorred the pollution of their bloud, and called upon thee for aid,</hi> &amp;c. Can we think this pious <hi>Amazon,</hi> had ever read <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> cenſure of that fact of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> and his curſe upon it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.5, 6, 7. even while he was <hi>bleſſing</hi> the reſt of his Sons (except inceſtuous <hi>Reuben</hi>) at the very point of death? <hi>Simeon and Levi are brethren, inſtruments of cruelty are in their habitations. O my ſoul, come not thou into their ſecret: unto their aſſembly, mine honour, be not thou united: for in their anger they ſlew a man, and in their ſelf-will they digg'd down a wall. Curſed be their anger, for it was fierce; and their wrath, for it was cruel. I will divide them in Jacob, and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them in Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The reſt of her prayer is conformable to this. Therefore ſhe prayeth, ver. 10. (in reference to <hi>Holofernes</hi> and his men) <hi>ſmite by the deceit of my lips</hi> (for ſhe meant to deſtroy him by lying) <hi>the ſervant with the prince, and the prince with his ſervant,</hi> &amp;c. And in ver. 13. <hi>Make my ſpeech and deceit to be their wound and ſtripe,</hi> &amp;c. Was not this a brave reſolution, a pious petition, to <hi>tell a lye for God?</hi> We forbear more inſtances, becauſe we delight not to ſcrape in ſuch Dung-hills. We have done with the <hi>Kalendar.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:116869:14"/>
                  <head>II. <hi>Of the</hi> RUBRICKS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bricks</hi> are Directions given in the Common-Prayer-Book, how to officiate and read the ſaid Book, in the ſeveral parts thereof. And they are called <hi>Rubricks,</hi> becauſe anciently printed in <hi>Red Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters;</hi> and are as much eſtabliſhed by Law, as any other part of the Book of Common-Prayer it ſelf. I ſhall inſtance onely in ſome of them, not medling with thoſe before noted in the inſerted Paper of <hi>Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. There are many <hi>Rubricks</hi> wherein the Miniſter is called <hi>Prieſt,</hi> which is the old Stile and Title in the Maſs-Book, from whence it was taken. We never finde it in the New Teſtament; but onely in the Old: which Title was then given to ſuch of the <hi>Levites</hi> as were made Prieſts to ſacrifice at the <hi>Altar.</hi> And thence the Papiſts borrowed that name for their Popiſh Sacrificers at their Altars. It is now then, a meer Superſtitious and Antichriſtian Name, no way warranted by the Word of God, in the Pontifician Senſe; yet is it uſed above fifty times in our <hi>Liturgy.</hi> It is true, one ſeeks to excuſe it by ſaying, Uſe hath made this ſo Popular, as it is not ſafe to remove it; yet, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it may be altered without prejudice to Religion. But why may not the Word <hi>Prieſt</hi> be taken away, and the word <hi>Miniſter</hi> put in the room? The Name of <hi>Miniſter</hi> is not unknown: yea, it is as often uſed in the <hi>Rubricks</hi> of the ſame Book, as the name <hi>Prieſt.</hi> Therefore it may, without the leaſt danger, or offence, be wholly obliterated. Hence it is, that in the Scots Liturgy it is wholly omitted, and <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> put into the room thereof. Whereas this is a more ſtrange and unknown name, being borrowed from the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which was never uſed to ſignifie a Prieſt, but an Elder, and thence borrowed to denote a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> as all the Learned know: and none but Papiſts uſe the word Prieſt; unleſs Scoffers at Miniſters, whom in ſcorn and deriſion they call and nick-name, <hi>Prieſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the fifth <hi>Rubrick</hi> of the <hi>Order for reading of the holy Scripture,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>That the Collect, Epiſtle and Goſpel appointed for the Sunday, ſhall ſerve all the week after, except there fall ſome Feaſt that hath his proper.</hi> By vertue of this, theſe in <hi>Cathedrals</hi> were read every day, albeit they had no <hi>Communions.</hi> But another <hi>Rubrick</hi> prefixed to the <hi>Epiſtles and Goſpels,</hi> runs thus: <hi>The Collects, Epiſtles and Goſpels to be uſed at the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116869:14"/>of the Lords Supper, and holy Communion, throughout the year.</hi> Theſe therefore were never intended to be read, but when there is the Sacrament of the Lords Supper adminiſtred. This was anciently adminiſtred every day, in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and ſo, to be uſed ſtill, at leaſt in <hi>Cathedrals,</hi> as appears by the Rubrick after the firſt <hi>Exhortation at the Communion.</hi> If then, upon any reaſonable cauſe, there be no Communion, there ought at that time to be no <hi>Epiſtle</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> read. If there be any read, it is without warrant. So that theſe two <hi>Rubricks</hi> fight; and which to follow, is uncertain. And indeed, they are both but blind guides that lead into the ditch, and make a man obnoxious to the Law.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The <hi>Rubrick</hi> before the <hi>general Confeſſion at the Communion,</hi> runs thus: <hi>Then ſhall this general Confeſſion be made in the name of all thoſe that are to receive the holy Communion, either by one of them, or elſe by one of the Miniſters.</hi> This gives liberty to Lay, or private men to offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate, in part at leaſt, as to this <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> which is a branch of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice peculiar to the Miniſter, to be <hi>the mouth of the people unto God in Prayer;</hi> eſpecially in the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, in the Congregation. What is this but to admit a private perſon to aſſiſt and bear a ſhare in adminiſtring the <hi>Lords Supper?</hi> Is not this to hit againſt the 17 <hi>Article</hi> of Religion, which declares it to be <hi>unlawful</hi> to any but ſuch as be <hi>lawfully called, and ſent;</hi> to wit, <hi>Miniſters</hi> duly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained? In all other parts of the Liturgy, all <hi>Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> are expreſly put upon the Miniſter alone, at leaſt to begin, and lead the Congregation therein.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In the Rubricks before the <hi>proper Prefaces</hi> at the Communion, it is ſaid, that <hi>upon Chriſtmas day, and ſeven days after;</hi> upon <hi>Eaſter-day,</hi> and <hi>ſeven days</hi> after; upon the <hi>Aſcention-day,</hi> and <hi>ſeven days</hi> after; upon <hi>Whitſon-day,</hi> and <hi>ſix days</hi> after, the ſame ſeveral <hi>Prefaces</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for each of theſe ſolemn days, ſhall be read; as if every of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven days following were one and the ſame with the firſt; and, what was done on the firſt day, was done over again every one of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing days: which yet was never done but once; and, but upon one day, at all; and perhaps, upon neither of thoſe days on which it is ſaid there to be done. But, of this, more, when we come to ſpeak of the <hi>Body</hi> of the Book.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The laſt <hi>Rubrick</hi> after the Communion, ſaith, <hi>Note, that every Pariſhioner ſhall communicate at the leaſt three times in the year, of which Eaſter to be one; and ſhall alſo receive the Sacraments, and other rites,</hi> &amp;c. But, the firſt <hi>Exhortation</hi> before the Communion, to be uſed when the people are <hi>negligent to come unto it,</hi> requireth the Miniſter to ſay unto the whole Congregation, <hi>I bid you all that be here preſent, and beſeech you for the Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, that ye will not refuſe to come thereto, being ſo lovingly called and bidden of God himſelf.</hi> Yet the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116869:15"/>
                     <hi>Rubrick</hi> ſeems to diſpenſe with Gods own Invitation: How rightly, let all ſober men conſider. And if thrice communicating will ſuffice, (contrary to the Primitive Practiſe, which was, for all to Communicate at every ſolemn meeting) why muſt <hi>Eaſter</hi> be one of the <hi>three times,</hi> more then any other <hi>Lords Day,</hi> ſeeing every <hi>Lords Day</hi> is celebrated upon the ſame account that that called Eaſter-day, is, <hi>viz.</hi> in memory of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of our Lord?</p>
                  <p>But where it is added in that <hi>Rubrick,</hi> He ſhall alſo <hi>receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and other rites,</hi> &amp;c. this is no other but non-ſenſe, or worſe. For, what <hi>Sacraments</hi> elſe are there for a Communicant of the Lords Supper to receive? Is <hi>Baptiſm</hi> to be reiterated? are the Popiſh Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments to be recalled? And if they were, muſt every Pariſhioner receive them; and that <hi>thrice a year?</hi> And what are the <hi>Rites</hi> he muſt receive? Be they <hi>Ceremonies? Humane Inventions? Superſtitious an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Croſſings; duckings, bowing to the Altar, towards the Eaſt, to Images,</hi> &amp;c? If ſo, where are theſe, or any of theſe enjoyned? And, if not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, why muſt they be all received thrice a year; or, at all? But of this, more hereafter.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The laſt <hi>Rubrick</hi> before the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> in order to <hi>Confirmation,</hi> concludeth thus: <hi>And that no man ſhall think that any detriment ſhall come to children by deferring of their Confirmation, he ſhall know for truth, that it is certain by Gods Word, that children being baptized, have all things neceſſary for their ſalvation, and be undoubtedly ſaved.</hi> Where is that <hi>Word of God?</hi> This cannot be underſtood of Children, after Baptiſm, dying in Infancy; for it ſpeaks of ſuch as are capable of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation;</hi> and, of Confirmation <hi>deferred.</hi> This ſuppoſeth their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a good while after <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> even till they come to ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and are able to give ſome good account of the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> (elſe can they not be admitted to Confirmation, as appears by the firſt <hi>Rubrick</hi> before Confirmation:) before which time, they may be guilty of many actual ſins; every of which (without true repentance) makes lyable to Condemnation. So that this Rubrick gives to Children once baptiſed, more aſſurance of their <hi>undoubted ſalvation,</hi> than ever God hath given them. For, if they be baptiſed, let them live or die, be godly or wicked, they muſt <hi>know for truth, that it is certain,</hi> (but not by Gods Word:) they <hi>not onely have all things</hi> (on Gods part) <hi>neceſſary to ſalvation;</hi> but, are <hi>undoubtedly ſaved.</hi> Is this a truth?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Rubrick after <hi>Matrimony,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The new-married perſons the ſame day of their marriage, M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ST receive the holy Communion.</hi> Who do ſo? what neceſſity of ſo doing? And if they do not ſo, who ſhall be puniſhed for their omiſſion? The Miniſter, if any body; becauſe he is bound to do all things according to the Book, if eſtabliſhed; and <hi>not otherwiſe.</hi> And if the marryed Perſons will not receive, what can the <hi>Miniſter</hi> do? As for the marryed perſons, they (by the <hi>Rubrick</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116869:15"/>before mentioned) are not bound to receive above thrice in one year: which, if they do, they need not receive on their <hi>marriage-day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. In the laſt <hi>Rubrick</hi> after <hi>Communion of the ſick,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>In the time of the Plague, Sweat, or ſuch other like contagious times of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes or Diſeaſes, when none of the Pariſh, or Neighbours, can be gotten to communicate with the ſick in their Houſes, for fear of the Infection, upon ſpecial requeſt of the diſeaſed, the Miniſter may onely communicate with him.</hi> By this, the Miniſter is bound not onely to viſit every perſon ſick of the <hi>Plague,</hi> &amp;c. (ſtanding at ſome diſtance) but, to adminiſter the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> alſo to him, if he deſire it; and that <hi>alone,</hi> if none elſe will joyn, as it is not to be expected they ſhould. This is no way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> or common <hi>Humanity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not to <hi>Chriſtianity:</hi> for, firſt, the very nature of the Sacrament re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a publick Adminiſtration, becauſe there muſt be a Communion of more then two perſons in the receiving of it. This appears plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſeveral other <hi>Rubricks</hi> of the ſame Book. For, 1. in the firſt <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> after the publick Communion, it is ordered, that, <hi>if there be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twenty perſons in the Pariſh, of diſcretion to receive the Communion, yet there ſhall be no Communion, except four, or three at the leaſt communicate with the Prieſt.</hi> If it be ſaid, this is the Order for Publick Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; but, it concerns not Private Communions of the ſick: it is anſwered, 1. that it appears not by the Word, that there is any <hi>war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> much leſs <hi>neceſſity</hi> for ſuch private <hi>Communions:</hi> for, the firſt <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> after Communion of the ſick, directeth the Miniſter thus: <hi>If a man, either by extremity of ſickneſs, or for want of warning in due time to the Curate, or for lack of company to receive with him, or by any other juſt impediment, do not receive the Sacrament of Chriſts Body and Blood; then the Curate ſhall inſtruct him, that if he do truly repent of his ſins, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly believe that Jeſus Chriſt hath ſuffered death upon the Croſs for him, and ſhed his Blood for his Redemption, earneſtly remembring the benefits he hath thereby, and giving him hearty thanks therefore,</hi> (without all which, what good will be get by receiving the Sacrament?) <hi>he doth eat and drink the Body and Blood of our Saviour Chriſt profitably to his ſouls health, although he do not receive the Sacrament with his mouth.</hi> 2. In the <hi>Rubrick</hi> before the <hi>Communion of the ſick,</hi> this Order is given, that the <hi>Curate</hi> having <hi>knowledge over night, or early in the morning,</hi> of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the ſick perſon to receive the <hi>Communion,</hi> and being ſignified <hi>alſo how many be appointed to communicate with him, and having a conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient place in the ſick mans houſe, where the Curate may reverently mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and a good number to receive the Communion with the ſick perſon, with all things neceſſary for the ſame, he ſhall there miniſter the holy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Therefore by theſe <hi>Rubricks,</hi> no <hi>Communion</hi> is to be miniſtred to the ſick, where there be but two to receive it.</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116869:16"/>
                  <p>Secondly, This is alſo no way agreeable to <hi>Humanity.</hi> Muſt a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, who hath the charge of many ſouls, adventure his health, and life, to gratifie an infectious perſon in that which (as by what hath been before alledged) is no way of neceſſity to the fick mans ſalvation? Muſt the Miniſter do this, or be puniſhed with <hi>Deprivation,</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? What cruelty is this? Nay, the very <hi>Canons</hi> of 1603. <hi>Can.</hi> 67. provided more mercifully then ſo; which runs thus: <hi>When any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is dangerouſly ſick in any Pariſh, the Miniſter or Curate (having know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof) ſhall reſort to him or her, (if the Diſeaſe be not known, or probably ſuſpected to be infectious) to inſtruct and comfort them,</hi> &amp;c. Here is a Diſpenſation in caſe of the <hi>Plague,</hi> or other <hi>infectious diſeaſe,</hi> for ſo much as <hi>viſiting the ſick:</hi> and no word at all of giving the <hi>Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</hi> So much ſhall at preſent ſuffice to be ſpoken of the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III. <hi>Of the Body of the Book.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. THe firſt words of it, (which the Miniſter is to read) are theſe: <hi>At what time ſoever a ſinner doth repent him of his ſin from the bottom of his heart, I will put all his wickedneſs out of my remembrance, ſaith the Lord.</hi> This is (in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> before it) called, <hi>A ſentence of Scripture:</hi> and the place alledged is <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.22. But that Text runs otherwiſe in the Original, and in the new Tranſlation of the Bible; <hi>viz. But if the wicked will turn from all his ſins that he hath committed, and keep all my ſtatutes, and do that which is lawful &amp; right, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not die. All his tranſgreſſions that he hath committed, they ſhall not be mentioned unto him: in his righteouſneſs that he hath done, he ſhall live.</hi> Here is little harmony between the <hi>Service-Book</hi> and <hi>Gods Book:</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſidering the very firſt words in the <hi>Liturgy, At what time ſoever.</hi> Which hath no warrant from that Text, and is diſſonant from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, [<hi>To day if ye will hear his voice,</hi> &amp;c.] and from that Application of it, <hi>Take heed, brethren, leſt there be in any of you an evil heart of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, in departing from the living God; but exhort one another dayly, while it is called</hi> To Day, <hi>leſt any of you be hardened through the deceitfulneſs of ſin.</hi> Moſt men are convinced of the neceſſity of <hi>repenting:</hi> but, ſuch is the <hi>deceitfulneſs</hi> of their hearts, that too many defer it, and that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that very ground expreſſed in theſe words, (which have no ground or warrant from the Word of God) <hi>At what time ſoever a ſinner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penteth,</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:116869:16"/>&amp;c. as if he could <hi>repent</hi> when he liſt; which carries many to Hell.</p>
                  <p>It is true, this is ſeemingly put off by a great Doctor, thus:
<note place="margin">D. P. de <hi>Diſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Eccl.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Sect. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Dixit Dominus quoad ſenſum, licet non verbatim.</hi> The Book ſpeaks the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> although not the very words of the Text. But this is too frigid an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to ſatisfie the Objection. For, 1. It is ſaid to be <hi>a ſentence of Scripture;</hi> not an <hi>Exhortation</hi> according to the <hi>ſenſe</hi> onely. It is one thing to give the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> another to repeat the words. 2. This agrees not with the <hi>ſenſe,</hi> but is contrary thereunto, as was but now demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Therefore it is untrue and injurious to charge the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> with the like, in alledging the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament in the <hi>New.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That expreſſion in the <hi>general Confeſſion of ſins,</hi> viz. <hi>There is no health in us,</hi> (although well meant) is incongruous, and improper, becauſe moſt of the common ſort underſtand not the true meaning of it; yet patter it over, out of cuſtom, without being (through their ignorance) duly ſenſible of what is indeed intended by it. Howbeit, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> may not alter the Phraſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. After the <hi>firſt Leſſon,</hi> at Morn. Prayer, <hi>Te Deum,</hi> or, <hi>Benedicite,</hi> (both of them, being <hi>Apochrypals</hi>) are to be read before the <hi>ſecond</hi> Leſſon; and ſo they interrupt the <hi>continued reading of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> which, the <hi>Preface</hi> to that Book would bear us in hand, is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt.</p>
                  <p>As for <hi>Te Deum;</hi> or, <hi>We praiſe thee, O God,</hi> &amp;c. it is a piece taken out of the <hi>Maſs-Book;</hi> and in <hi>Popiſh</hi> Churches uſually ſung, at times of great Victories, Deliverances, and other Triumphs. From thence, ſome Biſhops (little to their credit) have introduced it, upon like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, into <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches: that being no where enjoyned, nor warranted by any Law in force.</p>
                  <p>This ſhews what able men ſuch Biſhops are to govern, that know not how to expreſs their thankſgiving to God for any extraordinary mercy, ſo well, as in a ſuperſtitious formal dreſs uſually ſung in Popiſh Churches. And, as for <hi>Benedicite,</hi> viz. <hi>O all ye works of the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. it is a piece of the <hi>Maſs</hi>-Book alſo, and taken out of the <hi>Apocryphal ſong of the three Children.</hi> And it is bungled too; not ſet forth as it is in the <hi>Song</hi> it ſelf, as by comparing them may appear. And whereas that <hi>Song</hi> is ſaid, in the Title of it, in the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> to be <hi>the ſong of the three holy Children which followeth in the third of</hi> Daniel, <hi>after this place; [And they walked in the midſt of the fire, praiſing God, and bleſſing the Lord,]</hi> this is an abuſing, and belying of the Canonical Text, in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> 3. in which there is no hint of any ſuch thing. Yet muſt this come in, and be kept in, in our <hi>Liturgy</hi> (though, caſt out of the <hi>Scotch Book</hi>) to give another lye to the <hi>Preface</hi> of our Book of Common-Prayer; of which, more by and by.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The many <hi>Antiphonies</hi> &amp; <hi>Reſponds</hi> (except the peoples ſaying, <hi>Amen</hi>)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116869:17"/>have no pattern or warrant in the Word. Yet above an hundred of theſe <hi>Antiphonies</hi> and <hi>Reſponſals,</hi> or <hi>Anſwerings</hi> between Miniſter, Clerk and people, are enjoyned to be uſed; beſide the accompanying of him, in the <hi>Confeſſion of ſins, Creed,</hi> reading every other verſe of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> &amp;c. How can ſuch things (having no warrant in the Word) be done in Faith, in the Publique Worſhip of God; and not rather be accounted <hi>Will-Worſhip?</hi> This is the rather to be excepted againſt, not onely becauſe it is ſo frequent in the <hi>Maſs</hi>-Books, (but, no where elſe;) but becauſe alſo the <hi>Preface</hi> to the Book of Common-Prayer, ſaith, That <hi>the reading of the holy Scripture is</hi> (therein) <hi>ſo ſet forth, that all things ſhall be done in order, without breaking one piece thereof from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother:</hi> and <hi>for this cauſe, be cut off Antiphonies, Reſponds, Invitatories, and ſuch like things as did break the continual courſe of the reading of the Scripture.</hi> How then, do ſo many <hi>Reſponds</hi> and Anſwers of <hi>Clerk</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> while the Miniſter is reading; as likewiſe thoſe <hi>Anthems</hi> before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, which interpoſe between the firſt and ſecond <hi>Leſſon</hi> (all which are ſtill continued in the <hi>Book</hi>) agree with that <hi>Preface</hi> ſtill printed with the Book?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If the <hi>Letany</hi> muſt be read (which contains petitions for more particulars then all the Book beſides; and, being put into one conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued prayer, without ſo many interpoſitions and interruptions, might be of far better uſe then now it is) why muſt the <hi>praying part</hi> be ſo much performed by the People, and not by the Miniſter, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Office it is in publique, to pray for the people as their mouth; and not they to be his mouth? There is no ground for this in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: yet we muſt be made to believe, that there is <hi>nothing</hi> in the <hi>Leiturgy,</hi> but <hi>what is evidently grounded upon the Word.</hi> And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt that clauſe in the <hi>Let any [from the tyranny of the Biſhop of Rome, and all his deteſtable Enormities]</hi> be ſtill left out? was there no fear of his return to tyrannize over this Land again? Had he ever more Inſtruments at Work in this Kingdom ſince the Reformation, then now? If it be ſaid, The Act for <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> gives notice of an <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration</hi> in the <hi>Letany:</hi> yet, that <hi>Act</hi> doth not tell us what that is in particular. Therefore, till that <hi>alteration</hi> be named, that clauſe needeth not, yea ought not, to be omitted, ſo long as the <hi>Letany</hi> is uſed.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. In the Book printed in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> there be added (after the <hi>Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>) two Prayers; one for the then <hi>Queen,</hi> another for <hi>Biſhops</hi> (both which were prayed for before, in the <hi>Letany,</hi> and alſo in the Prayer at the <hi>Communion for the whole eſtate of Chriſts Church</hi>) which are not in the Book of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. And, in 1 <hi>Jac.</hi> theſe were continued, with one other Prayer for Queen <hi>Anne,</hi> the <hi>Prince,</hi> &amp;c. Now, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Prayers for the <hi>King, Queen,</hi> and <hi>Royal Family</hi> be uſeful, and neceſſary; yet, when the Act of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. admits of no alterations from, or additions to that Book in 5.6. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. ſave only in <hi>proper Leſſons
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116869:17"/>for</hi> Sundays, one in the <hi>Letany,</hi> and two more in the <hi>Communion;</hi> and, <hi>none other, or otherwiſe;</hi> how can thoſe Prayers be uſed, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them that uſe them liable to the Law (if rigorouſly urged,) till they be confirmed by Act of Parliament; Or rather, till that Act of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. be repealed and taken away?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Albeit the <hi>Preface</hi> to the Book, ſaith, that therein, <hi>many things be left out, whereof ſome be untrue, ſome uncertain, ſome vain, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious, and nothing is ordained to be read but the very pure Word of God, the holy Scriptures, or that which is evidently grounded upon the ſame:</hi> yet are there ſundry things more, in the <hi>Body</hi> of that Book, which are neither <hi>certain,</hi> nor <hi>true,</hi> nor <hi>evidently grounded on the Word.</hi> For, to omit the imperfect and corrupt <hi>Tranſlations</hi> mentioned before in the <hi>Sheet</hi> of Paper inſerted into this preſent Book; and, many more, not therein cited, (which ſhew there is too much, which is not the <hi>very pure Word</hi> of God:) it is too too palpable, that, in the <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Prefaces</hi> for <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day, and <hi>Whitſunday</hi> (as they are called) there are ſome things not only <hi>uncertain,</hi> but <hi>falſe;</hi> yea, impoſſible to be <hi>true;</hi> and therefore, not <hi>evidently grounded upon the</hi> Word of God. In the Collect or Prayer for <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day and <hi>ſeven days after,</hi> we muſt, in <hi>prayer,</hi> ſay unto God, that he hath given Chriſt, <hi>this day</hi> (<hi>viz. Decemb.</hi> 25.) <hi>to be born of a pure Virgin.</hi> On what Scripture is this (<hi>viz.</hi> that he was born that very day) <hi>evidently grounded?</hi> and, if it did ſo appear; how can we ſay the ſame (without manifeſt and groſs lying unto God) ſeven other days more, one after another, ſeeing he was born but once, and on one day onely? The like muſt be ſaid of the <hi>proper Preface,</hi> for that Day; of which before, in the <hi>Rubricks.</hi> Such alſo is the Collect for <hi>Whitſunday,</hi> which begins thus: <hi>God which as upon this day,</hi> &amp;c. And, more clearly, in the <hi>Proper Preface,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt came down this day from heaven,</hi> &amp;c. And this muſt be ſaid not only on that day, but on <hi>ſix days after.</hi> Can this be true, when he came down in that manner, but once? And, when that day was, is very <hi>uncertain;</hi> eſpecially with us, with whom <hi>Whitſunday</hi> is a <hi>Moveable Feaſt,</hi> falling out (as <hi>Lent,</hi> and <hi>Eaſter</hi> do) ſome years in one month; ſome, in another; but never on the ſame day of the ſame month, two years together, What horrible abuſing of God, and that in very Prayers, is this?</p>
                  <p n="8">8. After the <hi>Proper Prefaces</hi> at the Communion, followeth this: <hi>Therefore with Angels, and Archangels, and with all the Company of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, we laud and magnifie thy glorious Name,</hi> &amp;c. Here is another <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty</hi> (to ſay nothing of the <hi>untruth</hi> of it;) for the Scripture ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeaks of more <hi>Archangels</hi> then one: which is mentioned, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16. This one, was <hi>Michael, Jude</hi> 12. to wit, Chriſt, the <hi>Prince</hi> of his people, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.21. which moſt, if not all, expound of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Him who is mentioned in <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.7. where it is ſaid, There
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116869:18"/>
                     <hi>was war in heaven, Michael and his Angels fought againſt the Dragon, and the Dragon fought and his Angels, and prevailed not,</hi> &amp;c. It is true, that the ſuppoſititious <hi>Dionyſius Areopagita,</hi> takes upon him, in his <hi>Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial Hierarchy,</hi> to divide the Angels into three ſeveral <hi>Hierarchies:</hi> but, <hi>Quo warranto,</hi> further then his own bare word, he doth not at all ſo much as propound; only he pretendeth to take it from <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. (of which interpretations, ſee <hi>Zanch.</hi> in <hi>Epheſ.</hi>) that expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition being a meer dream.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. In one of the <hi>Prayers</hi> after the <hi>Communion,</hi> it is prayed, that <hi>thoſe things which for our unworthineſs we dare not, and for our blindneſs, we cannot ask, vouchſafe to give us,</hi> &amp;c. This is a <hi>Contradiction:</hi> for, while we ſay <hi>we dare not ask,</hi> we do <hi>ask,</hi> and pray him <hi>to give us.</hi> Can we pray thus in faith? Yes, you will ſay, when we pray for this, for <hi>the worthineſs of Chriſt,</hi> as after followeth. But then take this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. If our own <hi>unworthineſs</hi> cauſeth us not to <hi>dare to ask,</hi> why do we pray elſewhere, for ought elſe at all? It is not mans <hi>worthineſs,</hi> but Gods <hi>promiſe</hi> (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.18, 19. and <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 26, 27. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49) but eſpecially Chriſts warrant and command (<hi>Joh.</hi> 16.23, 24.) that gives us boldneſs, to <hi>dare to ask</hi> whatſoever we need.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. In the ſecond Prayer at <hi>publique Baptiſm,</hi> we pray, <hi>that Infants coming to Baptiſm, may receive remiſſion of their ſins by ſpiritual regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> How can this be? it is true, <hi>Remiſſion of ſins</hi> and <hi>regeneration,</hi> flow from one and the ſame fountain, and are both conveyed and <hi>ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> in Baptiſm, <hi>ſeminally</hi> at leaſt, to thoſe within the Covenant by the ſame <hi>Spirit.</hi> But <hi>remiſſion of ſins</hi> is not <hi>received</hi> by, or from <hi>ſpiritual Regeneration,</hi> but by, and from the <hi>bloud of Chriſt.</hi> For, <hi>without ſhedding of bloud there is no remiſſion,</hi> Heb. 9.22. that is to ſay, <hi>the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt cleanſeth us</hi> (in reſpect of guilt) <hi>from all ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. It is not then by the grace of <hi>regeneration</hi> wrought in us, but by the bloud of Chriſt ſhed for us, that we <hi>receive remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Away then with that expreſſion in Baptiſm; unleſs we be more for mans falſhood, then for Gods Truth.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. All that is in the <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> touching the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> was (contrary to the <hi>Act</hi> of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2.) added in King <hi>James</hi> his Reign, but never confirmed by Parliament, therefore not ſafely to be uſed, although ſomewhat in that kind be uſeful and neceſſary: yet not that model. The <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the firſt <hi>Queſtion</hi> [<hi>viz.</hi> to that, <hi>How many Sacraments hath Chriſt ordained in his Church?</hi>] is this, <hi>Two only as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally neceſſary to ſalvation:</hi> which <hi>Anſwer</hi> is very dubious, and liable to exception. For it may (without racking) be interpreted as a tacite admiſſion of more (as <hi>Marriage, Holy Orders,</hi> &amp;c.] though not <hi>generally neceſſary</hi> for all. Again, where it is demanded, <hi>why are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants baptized, when by reaſon of their tender age they cannot perform them?</hi> that is, they cannot <hi>repent,</hi> nor <hi>believe</hi> [which the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116869:18"/>the next preceding <hi>Queſtions,</hi> admits to be required <hi>of perſons that are to be baptized</hi>] the <hi>Anſwer</hi> is this: <hi>Yes, they do perform them by their Sureties,</hi> &amp;c. which is a meer tale. For, however the <hi>Sureties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> and engage for theſe, in behalf of the infant; and, upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, a charge (after <hi>Baptiſm</hi>) is given to the <hi>Sureties,</hi> to <hi>take care that the Infant, ſo ſoon as he is able to learn, be taught</hi> what he by them, <hi>vowed in</hi> Baptiſm, and what further is required of him: yet it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read or heard of in Scripture, that one man either <hi>repented,</hi> or <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved</hi> in the name and room of another, whereby that other did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all or any of the ſpiritual benefits, exhibited and ſealed in either of the Sacraments to ſuch as are admitted to them. And to ſay, the Infants <hi>perform</hi> (<hi>repentance</hi> and <hi>believing</hi>) by their <hi>Sureties,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Sureties vow them both in the Infants names,</hi> is a ſtrange and untrue expreſſion: for it is not <hi>vowing</hi> by one, that another ſhall <hi>repent,</hi> and believe, when he is not at preſent able to do either, that can truely be ſaid, to be a performing of them, by him that makes that vow; ſuppoſing him to be a true <hi>believer,</hi> which many Sureties be not.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. In the <hi>Commination</hi> appointed and <hi>enjoyned</hi> by the <hi>Rubrick</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, to be uſed <hi>divers times in the year,</hi> (however a learned Doctor would ſhift off the objection againſt it, by ſaying, <hi>Non tam exigitur quam conſulitur:</hi>) there is a <hi>ſervice</hi> ſet up, which, however it was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God to be once uſed by the children of Iſrael ſo ſoon as they <hi>were gone over Jordan</hi> into <hi>Canaan,</hi> Deut. 27. yet is now no way warrantable in the Publique Worſhip of God: that is, for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter openly to denounce Curſes upon all ſinners, <hi>divers times in the year;</hi> and that, not in the ordinary <hi>Reading-place,</hi> but <hi>out of the Pulpit:</hi> To which, <hi>all the people are required to ſay, Amen:</hi> Whereby many of them are neceſſitated to curſe themſelves. But, as for that place in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> that is no warrant for this, now; Becauſe, that was no part of the <hi>Publique Service</hi> then incumbent on the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or <hi>Levites,</hi> nor to be done by any in the place of Publique Worſhip: but upon Mount <hi>Ebal:</hi> and that by ſix of the <hi>Tribes,</hi> to wit, <hi>Reuben, Gad, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher, Zebulun, Dan and Naphtali,</hi> ver. 13. and that, but once. And let it be obſerved, that <hi>Levi</hi> was none of them that were appointed to <hi>Curſe;</hi> nor were they of that Tribe, ſo much as among them. But he was to be upon <hi>Mount Gerizzim,</hi> with <hi>Simcon, Judah, Iſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>char, Joſeph and Benjamin,</hi> to <hi>bleſs,</hi> ver. 12. And this was the charge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore given of God by <hi>Moſes</hi> unto <hi>Aaron and his ſons,</hi> (as their conſtant duty at all publique Aſſemblies of the Congregation for <hi>Worſhip</hi>) Numb. 6.23, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to bleſs the Congregation, thus: <hi>The Lord bleſs thee, and keep thee; the Lord make his face to ſhine upon thee, and be gracious unto thee; the Lord lift up his countenance upon thee, and give thee peace.</hi> This indeed was an Ordinance, to which God there promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a <hi>good</hi> ſucceſs, ſaying; <hi>They ſhall put my Name upon the children of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116869:19"/>Iſrael, and I will bleſs them.</hi> For Miniſters of the Goſpel then, whoſe Office it is to be Meſſengers of Peace, and to <hi>bring glad tidings of good things to his people;</hi> to be imployed, and that often, in <hi>curſing</hi> the people as a part of his Office and of publique Worſhip, (not this or that particular offender, being according to Chriſts Ordinance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, and cenſured, and ſtill remaining refractory and impenitent:) is ſuch a piece of humane and unchriſtian-like invention, as hath no warrant from the Word of God, nor from the practiſe of the <hi>Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church,</hi> which this very <hi>Commination</hi> it ſelf, in the firſt lines of it plainly confeſſeth, where it ſaith that, then the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> was, to put <hi>notorious ſinners</hi> to <hi>open penance,</hi> in <hi>Lent:</hi> and that, <hi>in ſtead thereof, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the ſaid Diſcipline may be reſtored, it is thought good,</hi> to uſe this. Which ſhews plainly, that this is no other then a later ſpawn of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in his Popiſh Services. More might be ſaid of ſundry other particulars in the <hi>Service-Book:</hi> but we ſuppoſe that he that ſhall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weigh that which hath been already noted, will think theſe enow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III. <hi>Of</hi> RITES <hi>and</hi> CEREMONIES.</head>
                  <p>HAving ſpoken of the neceſſity of Reformation in <hi>Worſhip,</hi> it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, in the next place, to ſhew the like neceſſity of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Rites and Ceremonies,</hi> which are appurtenances of, and appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to <hi>Worſhip,</hi> in relation to the Injunctions of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note>; and, <hi>to the uſe of edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.26.</note>.</p>
                  <p>And here we ſpeak not of <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which be <hi>Divine,</hi> by Gods own <hi>Inſtitution;</hi> for theſe are all, in ſome reſpects, parts of external Divine Worſhip, in their uſe, preſcribed by himſelf (ſuch are, the <hi>outward elements</hi> in the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c.) and, in other reſpects, <hi>Ceremonies</hi> appendent to that Worſhip, which is internal, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally intended in and by that which is external by Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
                  <p>But we ſpeak of <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> appointed by the Lights and Guides of the Church, for <hi>decency, order</hi> and <hi>edification;</hi> being of <hi>Humane</hi> inſtitution, and alterable, although uſed in the exerciſe of <hi>Religious Worſhip:</hi> according to the 34th <hi>Article</hi> of Religion, which teacheth that <hi>it is not</hi> neceſſary <hi>that Ceremonies be in all places one, or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116869:19"/>utterly like; for, at all times they have been divers, and may be changed, according to the diverſities of Countries, Times, and Mens man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The reaſons why ſuch <hi>Ceremonies</hi> not only may, but ſometimes muſt be <hi>changed, according to the diverſities of Countries, Times, and Mens manners,</hi> (which may make it evident that what is now deſired, no way tendeth to diſorder, confuſion, or <hi>Schiſm;</hi> but, to godly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, without the leaſt infringement of holy <hi>unity</hi> in the Church) are plainly ſet forth before the <hi>Book of Common-prayer</hi> it ſelf, under that <hi>Preface,</hi> or Title; <hi>Of Ceremonies, why ſome be aboliſhed, and ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</hi> Where it is ſaid, <hi>Of ſuch Ceremonies as be uſed in the Church, and have had their beginning by the inſtitution of man; ſome, at the firſt, were of godly intent and purpoſe deviſed, and yet at length turned to vanity and ſuperſtition; ſome entred into the Church by indiſcret Devotion, and ſuch a zeal as was without knowledge; and for becauſe they were winked at in the beginning, they grew daily to more and more abuſes, which not only for their unprofitableneſs, but becauſe they have much blinded the people, and obſcured the glory of God, are worthy to be cut away, and clean rejected.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Preface</hi> ſaith further, <hi>Some are put away, becauſe the great exceſs and multitude of them hath ſo increaſed in theſe later days, that the burden of them was intolerable: whereof St.</hi> Auguſtine <hi>in his time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, that they were grown to ſuch a number, that the eſtate of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an people was in worſe caſe concerning that matter, then were the Jews. And he counſelled that ſuch yoke and burthen ſhould be taken away, as time would ſerve quietly to do it. But what would St.</hi> Auguſtine <hi>have ſaid, if he had ſeen the Ceremonies</hi> of <hi>late days uſed among us, whereunto the multitude uſed in his time was not to be compared? This our exceſſive multitude of Ceremonies was ſo great, and many of them ſo dark, that they did more confound and darken, then declare and ſet forth Chriſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits unto us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon theſe and other reaſons it was, that many <hi>Ceremonies</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into the <hi>Maſs-Books</hi> and other Popiſh <hi>Breviaries,</hi> ſuch as, <hi>ducking</hi> and <hi>bowing</hi> to the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> to the Altar, the ſtanding up at <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> or <hi>Glory be to the Father,</hi> &amp;c. at the <hi>reading of the Goſpels</hi> of the Day, the wearing of <hi>Robes, Copes, Lawn ſleeves,</hi> or other <hi>Veſtments,</hi> (ſave onely a <hi>Rochet</hi> to be worn by an <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> or <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>Surplice only</hi> by <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi>) the wearing of <hi>Sandals</hi> or <hi>Slippers,</hi> when men go into <hi>Churches</hi> or <hi>Chappels;</hi> the <hi>turning Communion Tables,</hi> and ſetting them <hi>Altar-wiſe</hi> (at the <hi>Eaſt</hi> end of the <hi>Chan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>l,</hi> or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up <hi>Altars</hi> of ſtone in that place, whether the Congregation can hear or not:) womens wearing of <hi>Vails,</hi> and offering of <hi>Chriſomes</hi> at <hi>Churchings,</hi> and that at the <hi>high Altar;</hi> the reading of the <hi>Leſſons</hi> in one place, and the <hi>ſecond Service,</hi> at the <hi>Altar;</hi> which <hi>ſecond Service</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:116869:20"/>was never appointed by the <hi>Common-prayer-book</hi> to be uſed but onely at the celebration of the <hi>Lords Supper:</hi> the ſetting up of <hi>Tapers of wax, Candleſticks, Baſons</hi> and <hi>Ewres,</hi> upon the high <hi>Altar,</hi> and ducking to them every time a man comes into the Church or goes out, or ſtirs, while he is in it: (Whereas <hi>Cups, Pots and Baſons</hi> for Alms, were never ſince 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. to be ſet there, but at the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;</hi> nor then, to be bowed unto, though the Bread and Wine were on the Table;) The wearing of <hi>Hoods</hi> of degrees, and many other ſuch like devices, all which were laid aſide in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. as appears by the <hi>Rubricks,</hi> and the <hi>Act</hi> for Uniformity in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. compared together, which allows nothing but what was in the <hi>Book</hi> of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. ſave onely the <hi>alterations</hi> mentioned in the ſaid Act, as hath been before ſhewed. And, however the Rubrick before the Book printed in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> directeth to uſe ſuch Ornaments as were in uſe in 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. yet that is no part of the Book eſtabliſhed: becauſe the Book of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. hath no ſuch <hi>Rubrick;</hi> and the <hi>Act</hi> enjoyns all to be done according to that Book, <hi>and none other, or otherwiſe.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, afterwards, another Statute of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> did ſo appoint.</p>
                  <p>Now, the ſame <hi>Preface</hi> before the <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> touching Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, giveth all men to underſtand, that <hi>the moſt weighty cauſe of the aboliſhing of certain Ceremonies, was, that they were ſo far abuſed partly by the Superſtitious blindneſs of the rude and unlearned, and partly by the unſatiable avarice of ſuch as ſought more their own luere, then the glory of God, that the abuſes could not well be taken away, the thing remaining ſtill.</hi> Upon which grounds, there was a removal of them in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. For then, was that <hi>Preface</hi> of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> firſt prefixed to the <hi>Book of Common-prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſo great is the itch of mans corrupt nature after <hi>Humane</hi> inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Divine</hi> Worſhip, and ſo natural are Popiſh Gue-gaws and outward pompous toyes that pleaſe the ſenſes, that many of theſe (who had been laid aſide, as aboveſaid, in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.) and that, at the Conference at <hi>Hampton-court,</hi> it was deſired that thoſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Rites of the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm, kneeling at the Communion,</hi> the <hi>Surplice,</hi> &amp;c. might be put away; yet ſuch was the violence of the prevailing party at that time; that, having obtained Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe under the Great Seal, they in <hi>Convocation, An.</hi> 1603. recalled ſundry of thoſe rejected <hi>Ceremonies</hi> again; and enjoyned all Students in Colleges to wear <hi>Surplices</hi> in time of <hi>Divine ſervice,</hi> Can. 17. <hi>Copes</hi> by him that Miniſtreth the Sacrament; <hi>Epiſtolers</hi> and <hi>Goſpelers,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to 7. <hi>Eliz.</hi> (there being no ſuch Statute, nor <hi>Parliament</hi> in 7. <hi>Eliz.</hi>) and ſundry other things: under colour whereof, by degrees, moſt of thoſe things before caſt out, <hi>viz.</hi> bowing to the Eaſt, and to the <hi>Altar,</hi> with the reſt before named, were retroduced; and now devoutly (or rather ſuperſtitiouſly) obſerved, without any ſhew or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116869:20"/>colour of warrant, but <hi>ancient</hi> cuſtom, which being, duly examined, will appear to all to be firſt uſed in the Popiſh Churches, as too pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably appeareth by the <hi>Preface</hi> touching <hi>Ceremonies</hi> before al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</p>
                  <p>Yea, thoſe very men who are ſo much for theſe; and not onely urge the 18th <hi>Canon</hi> of 1603. but the <hi>Queens Injunctions</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">52 <hi>Injunct</hi>
                     </note> for <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Name of Jeſus,</hi> which no Common-prayer-book, or Statute hath enjoyned; yet, in other things, regard not thoſe <hi>Injunctions,</hi> nor the <hi>Book of Homilies;</hi> no, nor the <hi>Act for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> it ſelf touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch <hi>Ceremonies</hi> as they have a mind to recal and advance: wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs their ſetting up <hi>Candles</hi> in <hi>Candleſticks</hi> on the <hi>High Altar</hi> (as they call it) and ſuch like ſuperſtitions which the third <hi>Injunction</hi> of <hi>Eliz.</hi> reckons among thoſe things which <hi>tend to Idolatry and Superſtition, which of all other offences God doth moſt deteſt and abhor.</hi> They muſt have their <hi>Antiphonies, Reſponds,</hi> &amp;c. which the <hi>Preface</hi> to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer-book, tells us are laid aſide, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Not content with this, they muſt have all (except Candles lighted) that are upon the Popiſh Altars where <hi>Maſs</hi> is uſed, upon their high Altars; yea, <hi>piping</hi> on di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Inſtruments, <hi>ſinging</hi> (ſo as none can underſtand the <hi>matter,</hi> but onely be tickled with the <hi>muſick</hi>) <hi>playing upon Organs,</hi> &amp;c. all which were laid aſide in <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and even by the 2 <hi>Hom.</hi> of the <hi>Place and time of Prayer,</hi> (which is by vertue of <hi>Art.</hi> 35. ſubſcribed unto by every Miniſter in <hi>England</hi> that ever was admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, according to the Act of 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12.) are cenſured and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared openly to all, to be <hi>diſpleaſing unto God, and ſore and filthily to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file his holy Houſe and Place of Prayer.</hi> All which are here mentioned, to ſhew how far they deviate, and whither they are tending and poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amain, who under colour of upholding, and practiſing of the lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> do recal and retroduce many Popiſh <hi>Rites</hi> caſt out of this Church, and deſpiſe all Laws and Conſtitutions made againſt them; and are thereby lyable to Inditements every time they uſe them, upon the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. We ſhall forbear to inſiſt longer upon this, but leave it to others to judge what ſad and dangerous effects, theſe things (if they be ſuffered and countenanced) are likely to produce.</p>
                  <p>That which we chiefly aim at, is, to ſhew a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of reforming thoſe <hi>Rites and Ceremonies</hi> contained in the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the <hi>Canons</hi> of 1603. Such are, the <hi>Surplice, Copes,</hi> &amp;c. en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to be uſed by Miniſters; the <hi>Croſs</hi> in Baptiſm, <hi>Kneeling</hi> at the Communion, <hi>Marriage</hi> with the <hi>Ring, Bowing</hi> at the <hi>Name of Jeſus,</hi> and ſuch like, impoſed upon all, as eſtabliſhed by Law. But, ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhment, we do, and muſt deny, until we ſee a <hi>Record</hi> produced, by which that Book now in uſe, or printed in 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> is by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ratified and confirmed. For if either there be no <hi>Record,</hi> of that, to which an Act referreth, or that there be more alterations in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116869:21"/>the Book ſaid to be eſtabliſhed, than the <hi>Act</hi> mentioneth; can that Book be properly ſaid to be eſtabliſhed by Law, and not rather made void thereby? In all other things, nothing is admitted for Law, or as being of force by Law, but what is expreſly contained <hi>in verbis,</hi> in the Act it ſelf; eſpecially, if the Act refer to any thing to be confirmed by it, of which no Record can be produced, and which differs from ought elſe that is ſaid to be ratified by it. And this is the caſe of the preſent <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which neither is <hi>Recorded,</hi> nor agreeth with, but hath ſundry alterations from, and additions to that of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. beſides thoſe hinted in the <hi>Act</hi> of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. And if any <hi>Deed</hi> or <hi>Bond</hi> be raſed, or altered after ſealing; or, if raſed, or altered before ſealing, and that not witneſſed; will ſuch a <hi>Deed</hi> or <hi>Bond</hi> be admitted as good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence at Law, or in Equity, if produced and pleaded? We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot underſtand how the preſent Service-Book can be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law, it being no where Recorded; and, in ſundry things, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide thoſe mentioned in the Statute of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2.) varying from that which was once Recorded, as hath been before demonſtrated. To ſay, the Book, in what remaineth, ſtill bindeth, <hi>in tanto</hi> at leaſt, is but a miſtake: for, any Record, or <hi>Deed,</hi> vitiated in any one part, makes void the whole, in Law.</p>
                  <p>And as for thoſe <hi>Rites</hi> enjoyned in the Book of <hi>Canons,</hi> we ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to ſpeak of the Legality of them, till we come to ſhew the neceſſity of <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> a great part whereof is contained in that Book.</p>
                  <p>Nor is it our purpoſe to inſiſt upon the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of thoſe <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> ſo as to make any diſpute thereupon, nor to juſtifie or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thoſe who hold them ſimply unlawful in themſelves. But we, taking it for granted that they are in themſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>things indifferent,</hi> do humbly pray that theſe things may be duely conſidered, in the general:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That being ſuch, they ought not to be impoſed on thoſe, who cannot be <hi>fully perſwaded in their own minds</hi> and Conſciences that they are lawful, and therefore muſt ſin, if they uſe them. This is St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s own Doctrine and Practiſe touching things of this nature, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his own judgement of the lawfulneſs of them. In his days, many godly Chriſtians, both in <hi>Rome, Corinth,</hi> and elſewhere, made ſcruple of ſundry <hi>meats</hi> forbidden in the Levitical Law, and of omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>days</hi> enjoyned by it. Others, ſatisfied of the lawfulneſs of both, did eat thoſe <hi>meats,</hi> and omit thoſe <hi>days;</hi> at which others were ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized: ſome, by adventuring through other mens example, to do the like, albeit they were not fully ſatisfied of the lawfulneſs thereof, and thereby <hi>ſinned:</hi> others took offence, and were grieved, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon cenſured all that uſed their Chriſtian Liberty in thoſe things of which they that uſed it, were fully ſatisfied: and hereupon, the <hi>weak,</hi> for
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116869:21"/>cenſuring, ſinned alſo: and, by both theſe, the <hi>weak</hi> were in danger to be <hi>deſtroyed, Rom.</hi> 14.15.</p>
                  <p>Now, what was our <hi>Apoſtles Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Practiſe</hi> herein? His <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> was this: <hi>I know, and am perſwaded by the Lord Jeſus, that there is nothing unclean of it ſelf: but to him that eſteemeth any thing unclean, to him it is unclean,</hi> Rom. 14.15. And, <hi>All things indeed are pure; but, it is evil for that man who eateth with offence. It is good neither to eat fleſh, nor to drink wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother ſtumbleth, or is made weak,</hi> verſ. 20, 21. His <hi>Practiſe</hi> was this: 1. Touching himſelf; <hi>If meat make my brother to offend, I will eat no fleſh while the world ſtandeth, leſt I make my brother to offend,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.13. And, as toward others, he ſtraitly chargeth on all, theſe two things: 1. To take heed leſt by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>means this liberty of yours become a ſtumbling block to them that are weak,</hi> ibid. verſ. 9. that is, by uſing that Liberty before others not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in the lawfulneſs of it. 2. If the one will yet <hi>uſe this liberty,</hi> and the other will <hi>take offence,</hi> then, his charge is, <hi>Let not him that eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, deſpiſe him that eateth not; and let not him that eateth not, judge him that eateth,</hi> Rom. 14.3. But, as for enjoyning the <hi>eating</hi> of what him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf held to be lawful, on thoſe that doubted the lawfulneſs of it, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had more Authority then all our Biſhops and Clergy in <hi>Convocation,</hi> to make Canons) we never find that he did it; but, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and forbade all the very uſe of it, before any that, through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, took offence at it. If then, Authority will follow the Apoſtles rule, they will find a neceſſity, not onely of taking off all Impoſitions already made, but the taking away of all the things ſo impoſed, at which ſo many able and godly peaceable Miniſters and People do take offence; and, for which, ſo many thouſands have deeply ſuffered, to avoid ſinning againſt God by conforming to them. <hi>For, whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If it be ſaid, The inſtances laſt given concern onely private things, and private practiſes; what is this to Publick Order in the Houſe of God, where the <hi>Service and Worſhip of Almighty God, by the Hedge of Ceremonies is preſerved from lying open to all profaneneſs;</hi> as a confident ſtickler for <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> groundleſly pretendeth? To this, it is anſwered, That Ceremonies are no ſuch <hi>Hedge;</hi> unleſs to keep out ſuch as have as good right to the Ordinances as they who do impoſe them, (for which they muſt one day give a ſad account;) and, that it is much more dangerous and ſinful to enjoyn things of this nature for Publick uſe in the Adminiſtration of Publick Ordinances. Becauſe, thoſe private <hi>meats,</hi> &amp;c. may be avoided by ſuch as take offence at them; for, what neceſſity, to be preſent at the uſe of them? But, there is a neceſſity of being preſent at the other: which he that negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth, is lyable to puniſhment by the Law. The Law tyeth all to come to the Common Service, every Sunday, and Holy-day; to receive the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116869:22"/>Holy Communion thrice at leaſt in every year: and, impoſeth a ſharp penalty for neglect hereof. So that, while theſe are impoſed, or uſed, (where weak Chriſtians take offence at them) many godly men are forced to offend, either againſt God, by ſubmitting to that they are not ſatisfied in the lawfulneſs of it; or, againſt the Laws of the Land, by not conforming to them, which they cannot do without ſin. So that the <hi>impoſing</hi> of them upon all, or the <hi>uſing</hi> of them before all, who cannot, without ſin, ſubmit to them, is the abuſing of Authority, and the making it to ſin againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by putting it upon the forcing <hi>thoſe for whom Chriſt died, to ſin</hi> againſt their own Conſciences, and to drive them on to <hi>deſtruction</hi> in Hell, as a man would force a Beaſt into the water, or fire that will ſurely devour him. It is then a groundleſs <hi>put off,</hi> to ſay, that ſuch things <hi>being commanded by juſt Authority, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference by that command determineth, and they become neceſſary:</hi> which is quite contrary to the Apoſtles rule.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If theſe be retained in ſome places where no offence is taken at them: yet there is no reaſon to impoſe, or uſe them in other places where any are offended at them. For, 1. to plead Impoſition for order and unity in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is to no purpoſe; becauſe there is no neceſſity of the ſame, in all places, no more then of all the ſame Orders and Practiſes in all <hi>Corporations</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> and, of every <hi>Company</hi> within thoſe Corporations (who all have different Orders and Rules) to preſerve Order and Unity in the Civil Government of the Kingdom. 2. Our very Articles of Religion, (as hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) ſay,
<note place="margin">Art. 34.</note> That <hi>it is not neceſſary that Ceremonies be in all places one, or utterly like; for at all times they have been divers, and may be changed, according to the diverſities of Countries, times, and mens manners.</hi> 3. If it be ſaid, Theſe refer to <hi>different Countries;</hi> not to different <hi>places</hi> within the <hi>ſame Country:</hi> It is anſwered, that <hi>times, and mens manners,</hi> muſt produce a Change, where ever a removal of thoſe in being, is neceſſary, as appears by the Article. And where things of this nature, that <hi>at firſt were of godly intent and purpoſe deviſed, but at length turned into vanity and ſuperſtition;</hi> by the Preface touching <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies,</hi> (before cited) they are adjudged <hi>worthy to be cut away, and clean rejected:</hi> and ſo many of them have already been, (as was the <hi>Braſen</hi> Altar by <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>) And it further telleth us, that <hi>as thoſe be taken away which were moſt abuſed, and burdened mens conſciences with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe:</hi> ſo the <hi>other that remain may (upon juſt cauſes) be altered and changed.</hi> So that here is nothing deſired, in the taking away the impoſition, yea, all <hi>uſe</hi> of them, but according to Law.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Book of Common-Prayer of 2 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. is in ſome things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to, and particularly as to <hi>Ornaments</hi> and Rites, both by the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> before <hi>Morning-Prayer</hi> in the preſent Liturgy; and, by the Stat. of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. So that, as to this point, ſo much of that firſt Book is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116869:22"/>ſtill in force by Law. But, that Book hath expreſly given a liberty in ſome of the things here deſired to be no further impoſed, where (in the laſt Page thereof, called, <hi>Certain Notes for the more plain Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and decent Miniſtration, of things contained therein</hi>) it ſaith, <hi>As touching kneeling, croſſing, holding up of hands, knocking upon the breaſt, and other geſtures, they may be uſed or left, as every mans devotion ſerveth, without blame.</hi> This is ſtill good Law. So that whatever is enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Canons for the impoſing this, is void in Law by the Stat. of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8.19. (although made by the Kings <hi>Licence</hi> and <hi>Aſſent</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe contrary to that Law of 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. in this particular.</p>
                  <p>Now, if the Law it ſelf give a Liberty in ſome; we truſt that, upon the foregoing Reaſons, our <hi>Law-givers</hi> will take off the impoſition of the reſt, if not wholly remove them.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Biſhops themſelves take Liberty to omit one Ornament im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on them to be uſed: namely, the <hi>Paſtoral Staff,</hi> which in the ſame place of the Book of 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. he is enjoyned to <hi>have in his hand, or to have it born by his Chaplain;</hi> and this is not left Arbitrary, as the Rites laſt before named, are: yet the Biſhops herein can diſpenſe for themſelves: is there not reaſon then to diſpenſe with Miniſters in the reſt?</p>
                  <p>Having thus pleaded the neceſſity of Reformation in <hi>Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies</hi> (but eſpecially of providing againſt the Impoſition of any of them) in general; we ſhall not enter into any debate of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: for, of that there is no need in this place. But, becauſe we are ſubject to be upbraided, that many of us have both ſubſcribed to uſe all thoſe, contained in the Liturgy; and, ſome of us have accordingly uſed them: and that therefore we are Revolters from our <hi>Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and thereby lyable to the penalty of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> by the ſixth <hi>Canon:</hi> It behoves us to make this Apology for our ſelves. 1. That albeit ſome of us have unadviſedly ſubſcribed to uſe them, and perhaps have uſed them ſometimes; yet finding that many ſober Chriſtians are ſcandalized at them, we hold our ſelves bound to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Apoſtle; and, what he did in the Caſe of <hi>meat</hi> (which he held to be lawful) we muſt do, in the Caſe of <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> to uſe them no more <hi>while the world ſtandeth, rather then make our brother to offend.</hi> 2. As to the danger incurred thereby, we muſt not ſo much ſtand upon that, as to <hi>chuſe iniquity rather then affliction.</hi> 3. And as touching the validity and force of the <hi>Canon,</hi> we fear it not, it being void in Law: of which we ſhall ſpeak more under the head of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:116869:23"/>
               <head>IIII. <hi>Of</hi> CHURCH-GOVERNMENT.</head>
               <p>BY <hi>Church-Government</hi> is meant the <hi>Eccleſiaſtcal</hi> Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſaid, and commonly reputed to be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the Laws of the Realm. For, however ſome have of late pretended to a <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> or Divine Inſtitution of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> of late years uſed in <hi>England;</hi> yet the Laws of the Kingdom would never own any ſuch thing, nor ſuffer them to exerciſe any power, but what the <hi>Municipal</hi> Laws Authorize them unto. Yea, <hi>the Statute of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,</hi> 25th of <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>An.</hi> 1350. Declareth plainly that <hi>Prelacy</hi> it ſelf was erected in <hi>England</hi> by the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and not by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authority. For that Statute begins thus: <hi>Whereas late in the Parliament of good memory of</hi> Edward <hi>King of</hi> England, <hi>Grandfather to our Lord the King that now is, the five and twentieth year of his Reign, holden at</hi> Carlile, <hi>the Petition heard, put before the ſaid Grandfather and his Counſel in his ſaid Parliament by the Comminalty of the ſaid Realm, containing; That whereas the Holy Church of</hi> England <hi>was</hi> FOUND<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ED IN THE ESTATE OF PRELACIE <hi>within the Realm of</hi> England <hi>by the ſaid Grandfather, and his Progenitors, and the Earls, and other Nobles of his ſaid Realm, and their Anceſtors, to inform them and the people of the Law of God,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore, we cannot look upon ſuch Biſhops in any other Capacity, in <hi>England.</hi> And, according hereunto, take notice, under this Head of <hi>Church-government,</hi> 1. Of their <hi>Conſtitution</hi> by <hi>Conſecration;</hi> 2. Of their <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> by <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation</hi> of his Majeſty according to his Laws. 3. Of their <hi>Execution</hi> of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> accordingly. By their <hi>Conſecration,</hi> they have a power of <hi>Ordination.</hi> By their <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> they have a power to <hi>Govern.</hi> And, by their <hi>Execution</hi> of that Office, they have a power of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> But, all theſe, according to the Laws of the Land; and none other, or otherwiſe. We ſhall therefore ſpeak ſomewhat to each of theſe, and humbly offer Reaſons of the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>reforming</hi> Epiſcopacy and Church-government, in every one of theſe.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116869:23"/>
                  <head>I. <hi>Of the</hi> Conſecration <hi>of Biſhops, and their power of</hi> Ordination <hi>thereupon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <q>1. BY the Laws of the Land, after the death of any Biſhop,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dr.</hi> Heylin, <hi>Advertiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> Hiſt. <hi>of K.</hi> Charles, <hi>p.</hi> 193.</note> his Majeſty uſeth to ſend out his Writ of <hi>Conge d' Eſlier,</hi> to the Dean and Chapter to Elect another. Which Election being made, ſignified under the Chapter-Seal, and confirmed by the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Aſſent; the King ſendeth out his <hi>Mandate</hi> to the Archbiſhop of the Province, to proceed to <hi>Conſecration</hi> (of the perſon ſo elected) or <hi>Confirmation</hi> (if <hi>conſecrated</hi> before, and now but <hi>Tranſlated</hi> from one <hi>See</hi> to another) as the caſe may vary.</q> So is it acknowledged by one that takes on him to know more than many others of this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. But, whereas he addeth, that <hi>thereupon it muſt needs be, that when the Church comes to ſuch a condition</hi> (that is, to be without <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deans and Chapters;</hi> of both which the ſame Author ſaith, the late King was content (in the <hi>Confer.</hi> at the <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi>) to grant an abolition;) &amp;, that this was acknowledged on all ſides <hi>that where there is no</hi> Dean and Chapter <hi>to Elect,</hi> and <hi>no</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>to</hi> Conſecrate, and Confirm <hi>the Perſon elected; there can be legally, and regularly no ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Biſhops:</hi> There is no neceſſity of ſuch a Conſequence, nor of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king more <hi>Archbiſhops,</hi> or <hi>Deans and Chapters,</hi> or continuing of any ſuch, if it ſhall pleaſe the King and Parliament, by any <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Statute</hi> to appoint any other way and courſe of <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>Conſecration</hi> of Biſhops. Which is as eaſie to be done, as any thing elſe Enacted <hi>in</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; there being no Divine Right ſo much as pretended unto, for ſuch <hi>Election,</hi> or <hi>Conſecration</hi> as of late was uſed in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whereas it is of late much inſiſted upon, that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is not only an Office of <hi>Precedency</hi> and <hi>Preſidency</hi> above other <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> given to them by the free Election of the reſt; to regulate, order, and act things agreed upon by the Presbytery joyned with them, as the <hi>Commander</hi> in chief in an <hi>Army,</hi> as the <hi>Capital Juſtice</hi> in a <hi>Court,</hi> or as the <hi>Speaker</hi> in either Houſe of Parliament; but that it is a diſtinct and ſpecifical Order (by <hi>Divine Right</hi>) Superiour to all other Presbyters, which Order onely, is Authorized to exerciſe ſuch things as none elſe may medle with: We ſay, that this in <hi>England</hi> was never at all arrogated by any Biſhops, till of very late times. 2. The things they make peculiar to Biſhops, <hi>ratione Ordinis,</hi> are, <hi>ſole Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116869:24"/>and <hi>ſole Juriſdiction;</hi> as if none had power in either of theſe but themſelves: neither of which, even they who pretend to derive their <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> from the Apoſtles, ever undertook to make good by any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Antiquity. Yea, 3. thoſe very Antiquities which they allege, are either ſpurious, or elſe ſpeak nothing either of <hi>ſole Ordination,</hi> or of <hi>ſole Juriſdiction;</hi> but rather, the contrary; as might eaſily be made out. But, we tye our ſelves to ſpeak to theſe particulars only, as ſaid to be made out by Law.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This was never yielded by any Law of <hi>England;</hi> nor, by the Book of <hi>Ordination.</hi> For, however that Book eſtabliſhed in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and (after repeal by Queen <hi>Mary</hi>) confirmed in 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 1. Yet when it ſpeaks of the making of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> it calls that a <hi>Conſecration,</hi> and not an <hi>Ordination;</hi> as it doth, when it ſpeaks of making <hi>Deacons,</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> which it calleth <hi>Prieſts:</hi> calling one, <hi>The form and manner of Ordering Deacons;</hi> the other, <hi>The form of Ordering</hi> Prieſts. But when it ſpeaks of the other, it changeth this Word <hi>Ordering,</hi> and calls it, The form of <hi>Conſecrating an Archbiſhop, or Biſhop.</hi> Which ſhews plainly, that the Book of <hi>Ordination</hi> never meant to make Biſhops, or (as Dr. <hi>Gauden</hi> calls it) <hi>Legal Epiſcopacy,</hi> to be not only in <hi>Degree,</hi> and Office of <hi>Prolocutor,</hi> but in a diſtinct <hi>Order,</hi> of Chriſt's and his Apoſtles inſtitution, Superiour to a <hi>Presbyter.</hi> It is indeed an eaſie matter for a bold man to contradict this; and, to ſay, that <hi>the antient Writers call the Solemn form of conſecrating a Biſhop by no other name then that</hi> of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatio Epiſcopi:</hi> but, it ſeems, it is not ſo eaſie to prove what he ſaith. For he produceth no ſuch proof at all: ſo that this confident ſaying touching ſuch <hi>Ordination</hi> of Biſhops (affirmed by his Adverſary to be a <hi>Novel Popiſh Poſition</hi>) that this is <hi>[Not Novel, he is ſure]</hi> is but a meer ſhift, and a put off, no confutation at all. And, where he is pleaſed afterwards to urge the <hi>Preface</hi> to the Book of <hi>Ordination,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dr <hi>Heylin</hi> Certam. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtol. p. 143.</note> which men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth, <hi>three Orders of Miniſters in the Church; Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons;</hi> and, one paſſage in one of the <hi>Prayers,</hi> at the <hi>Conſecration</hi> of an <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> or <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to prove that Epiſcopacy is a diſtinct <hi>Order</hi> from, and Superiour to that of <hi>Presbyters:</hi> he muſt be intreated to take notice, 1. That the <hi>Preface</hi> alleged ſaith not (as he ſpeaks) <hi>theſe THREE Orders;</hi> but, onely, <hi>theſe Orders of Miniſters,</hi> &amp;c. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven there, by way of explanation, the <hi>Preface</hi> calls them <hi>Offices, [which Offices were evermore had in ſuch reverent eſtimation,</hi> &amp;c.] now we deny them not to be diſtinct <hi>Offices;</hi> only we cannot admit, in his ſenſe, the <hi>Office</hi> of a Biſhop to be a diſtinct <hi>Order,</hi> above <hi>Presbytery.</hi> For, even, in that very <hi>Preface,</hi> it ſpeaks of <hi>Conſecrating,</hi> not of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining</hi> a Biſhop, as the Book all along doth of <hi>Ordering,</hi> that is, <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining</hi> of <hi>Deacons</hi> and <hi>Prieſts:</hi> but never of other then of <hi>Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> that is, of ſetting them over the reſt in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116869:24"/>degree, to be the mouth and hand of the reſt, in executing what by the reſt is agreed upon. And 2. touching that <hi>Prayer</hi> he mentions, wherein <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is called, in that Part of the Book it ſelf which concerneth <hi>Biſhops, an Order:</hi> This is but a wyre-drawing of the Words, and a meer wreſting of them. The Words of the Prayer are theſe, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, giver of all good things, which by thy holy Spirit haſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted divers Orders of Miniſters in thy Church, mercifully behold this thy Servant, now called to the Work and Miniſtry of a Biſhop,</hi> &amp;c. Now, how do theſe words prove a Biſhop to be a diſtinct <hi>Order,</hi> when ſpeaking of the perſon then to be made Biſhop, it is not ſaid, he is called to the <hi>Order,</hi> but to the <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry of a Biſhop?</hi> And ſeeing he onely talks of <hi>antient Writers,</hi> but produceth none, we ſhall make bold to mind him what is the ſenſe of the <hi>Canon-Law</hi> (which he pleads to be ſtill in force in <hi>England</hi>) if <hi>Lindwood</hi> (that great Engliſh Canoniſt) be of any value with him; who ſaith expreſly, <hi>Epiſcopatus non eſt Ordo.</hi> Yea, the very Book of <hi>Ordination,</hi> in ordering of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> appointing 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. to be then read [<hi>If any deſire the Office of a Biſhop, he deſireth an honeſt work. A Biſhop muſt be blameleſs,</hi> &amp;c.] doth more then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citly admit a Biſhop and a Presbyter not to differ in Order. To which we ſhall add the judgement of an antient Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> even <hi>Anſelmus</hi> himſelf (an high man for the Pope, and a great Conteſtor with the King for Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, even beyond the bounds of the Laws of this Land) who in his <hi>Commentary</hi> on the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> where <hi>Paul,</hi> cap. 1. ſaluteth but two Orders, <hi>Biſhops and Deacons,</hi> on the word <hi>Epiſcopis,</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>Epiſcopis, id eſt, Presbyteris—Epiſcopos namque pro Presbyteris more ſuo poſuit. Non enim plures Epiſcopi in una civitate erant, neque Presbyteros intermitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, ut ad Diaconos deſcenderet. Sed dignitatem &amp; excellentiam Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terorum declarat, dum eoſdem qui Presbyteri ſunt, Epiſcopos eſſe manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat. Quod autem poſtea unus electus eſt, qui caeteris praeponeretur, in Schiſmatis remedio facium eſt, ne unuſquiſque ad ſe trahens Evangelium, rumperet. Nam eſt</hi> Alexandriae <hi>a</hi> Marco <hi>Evangeliſta uſque ad</hi> Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clam, <hi>&amp;</hi> Dionyſium <hi>Epiſcopos (qui ſederunt in Centuria</hi> 3.) <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum unum de ſe elecium, &amp; in Excelſiori loco &amp;</hi> Gradu <hi>collocatum Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum nominabant, quomodo ſi Exercitus, Imperatorem faciat, aut Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coni elegant de ſe, quem induſtrium noverint, &amp; Archidiaconum vocent. Conſtat ergo</hi> APOSTOLICA INSTITUTIONE, <hi>omnes Presbyteros eſſe Epiſcopos, licet nunc illi majores hoc nomen obtineant. Epiſcopus enim</hi> Superintendens <hi>dicitur: &amp; omnis Presbyter debet inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere curam ſuper oves ſibi commiſſas.</hi> For brevity ſake we forbear to Engliſh this long allegation. The ſum of it is, that in the Primitive Church, <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> were one, in reſpect of <hi>Order;</hi> however, a Biſhop choſen by the Presbytery were over them in reſpect of <hi>place</hi> and <hi>degree.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116869:25"/>4. <hi>Biſhops,</hi> being <hi>Conſecrated,</hi> have power by the <hi>Stat.</hi> of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. to <hi>Ordain</hi> both <hi>Deacons,</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> which the Book incongruouſly calleth <hi>Prieſts.</hi> But, whereas the Epiſcopal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty claimeth <hi>ſole Ordination,</hi> as if no Miniſter can be rightly Ordained, who is not ordained by a Biſhop; and, under this pretence, many of the preſent Prelatical Party ſtick not to degrade and unordain ſuch Miniſters as are Ordained by Presbyters alone (even where no Biſhops are allowed to execute that Office) and Schiſmatically to adviſe and perſwade all to withdraw from all Aſſemblies and Ordinances, as being no Ordinances of Chriſt, where ſuch Miniſters as are ordained onely by the <hi>Presbytery</hi> without a Biſhop, do adminiſter: We muſt give this Anſwer. 1. That there is no Scripture that appropriateth this to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops alone. 2. There are ſeveral warrants in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> to juſtifie the laying on of hands without a <hi>Biſhop</hi> in their ſenſe. When <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> (after called <hi>Paul</hi>) were to be ſent out to preach, the Holy Ghoſt commanded to <hi>ſeparate</hi> them for that <hi>Work;</hi> whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Simeon</hi> ſur-named <hi>Niger, Lucius</hi> of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> and <hi>Manaen</hi> (not one of them a Biſhop in our Prelatical Advocates ſenſe) <hi>laid hands on them,</hi> and <hi>ſent them forth,</hi> Acts 13. Thus, <hi>Timothee</hi> was ordained by <hi>the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands of the Presbytery,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.14. This made him a preaching <hi>Presbyter</hi> and <hi>Biſhop:</hi> although the laying on of <hi>Pauls hands</hi> made him an <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.6. 3. The Book of <hi>Ordination</hi> it ſelf, though it appoint the Biſhop to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the preſident and chief Actor; yet it allows him not to act (as in <hi>Confirmation</hi> of Children) alone, in the <hi>Ordaining</hi> of <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Prieſts;</hi> But, <hi>the Biſhop with the Prieſts preſent ſhall lay their hands ſeverally upon the head of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that receiveth Orders.</hi> So, the <hi>Rubrick:</hi> therefore no Biſhop hath ſole power of <hi>Ordination,</hi> nor may he <hi>Ordain alone.</hi> 4. That ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Statute of 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. which ratifieth the Book of <hi>Ordination,</hi> doth not tye all to that one Form, as appears by the Stat. of 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. which ſaith thus: <hi>Be it Enacted by the Authority of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That every perſon under the degree of a Biſhop, which doth, or, ſhall pretend to be a Prieſt or Miniſter of Gods holy Word and Sacraments, by reaſon of any other form of Inſtitution, Conſecration, or Ordering, then the form ſet forth by Parliament, in the time of the late King of moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy memory, King</hi> Edward <hi>the ſixth, or now uſed in the Reign of our moſt gracious Soveraign Lady, before the Feaſt of the Nativity next coming, ſhall in the preſence of the Biſhop—Subſcribe to all the Articles of Religion,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore the Law intended not to tye all to the form of <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> by Biſhops; but, tyeth Biſhops to give them Inſtitution if they ſubſcribe the <hi>Articles,</hi> and be otherwiſe qualified as that Act preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth. 5. This is to un-Church all the Proteſtant Churches in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, where there are no Biſhops; and, to deny them Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which hitherto hath owned them,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116869:25"/>and held Communion with them as true Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Now, in ſew words, we muſt a little take notice of the neceſſity of Reforming that Book it ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In the <hi>Preface.</hi> For, where that ſaith, <hi>It is evident unto all men diligently reading the holy Scripture, and ancient Authors, that from the Apoſtles time, there hath been theſe Orders of Miniſters in Chriſts Church, Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons:</hi> it hath been ſhewed before, that (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we read of <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>Elders,</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi>) theſe are not three diſtinct <hi>Orders</hi> of the Miniſtry; for that <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> are of the ſame <hi>Order.</hi> Nor are <hi>Presbyters, Prieſts:</hi> there being no ſuch <hi>name</hi> in the New Teſtament, nor any ſuch <hi>Office</hi> in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel. Now ſeeing, this <hi>Preface</hi> is ſo much made uſe of, and wreſted, to prove an untruth touching the diſtinction of <hi>Orders;</hi> and, gives ſuch a <hi>name</hi> to <hi>Miniſters,</hi> as argues them to be <hi>Sacerdotes Sacrificuli,</hi> ſacrificing <hi>Prieſts,</hi> (which is not ſo, but repugnant to their <hi>Office</hi>) it ought to be reformed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the <hi>Ordering</hi> of <hi>Deacons,</hi> the <hi>Biſhop (alone)</hi> is to lay on hands, whereas it is not ſo to be done in the <hi>Ordering</hi> of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> (as they are nick-named) or Conſecration of <hi>Biſhops.</hi> And this alſo is contrary to the practice of the Apoſtles themſelves, expreſſed in that very Scripture, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. appointed to be one of the Epiſtles to be read at that time; where, after <hi>chooſing</hi> the ſeven <hi>Deacons,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Theſe they ſet before the Apoſtles; and when they bad prayed, THEY</hi> (not, <hi>one</hi> of them) <hi>laid their hands on them.</hi> Now, ſeeing this was ſo; and, that at every Ordination of <hi>Deacons,</hi> other Miniſters, beſide the Biſhop, are preſent; and ſeeing further, it is ſaid in the third Prayer then uſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Letany, that God did <hi>inſpire his Apoſtles to chuſe to this Order</hi>— St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> with other; which directly croſſeth the Text, which ſaith, <hi>The whole multitude choſe them;</hi> and that by order from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: Why ſhould ſuch a practice be continued by a ſingle Biſhop, ſo contrary to that of the Apoſtles themſelves, and every other <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> in our own Church?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the Ordering of <hi>Prieſts.</hi> We ſay, as before, that Title or name of <hi>Prieſt,</hi> ought to be changed, for the Reaſons aboveſaid. But, that which moſt offendeth, is, that in the very act of <hi>Ordaining,</hi> the Biſhop takes upon him to give that, which none but God himſelf hath power to beſtow, where it ſaith, <hi>Receive the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c. which be the words of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf to his Apoſtles, without any warrant from him to be uſed by Biſhops, or any others. For, however <hi>Ordination</hi> be neceſſary, yet there can be no reaſon, that a Biſhop, or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſhould in this aſſume more in officiating, then in all other Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, where the words of <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> in <hi>Baptiſin,</hi> in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> &amp;c. are firſt rehearſed; and then, at the act
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116869:26"/>of miniſtring, a Prayer is uſed, not a Magiſterial uſe of the very words of Chriſt himſelf in the firſt inſtitution; as is obvious to all. This therefore ſavors of preſumption, not to be admitted in ſo holy an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: eſpecially, where a Biſhop ſhall (as by report, ſome now do) take upon him to <hi>breathe</hi> upon the perſon he ordaineth, as Chriſt did upon his Apoſtles. Moreover, it being now claimed as peculiar to <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> (as a diſtinct Order) to have the ſole <hi>power of Ordination,</hi> which hath been proved not to be ſo; It is requiſite that herein alſo ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration be made to the contrary, that we may not give offence to the Proteſtant Churches with whom we hold Communion; nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of ſuch an untruth among our ſelves, to which all muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. As for Conſecrating of <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> (in which the ſame Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. is read again, that was uſed in <hi>Ordaining of Prieſts;</hi> which ſheweth, that the Compilers of that Book never dreamt of a diſtinction of <hi>Orders</hi> between <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters)</hi> we onely ſay thus much, That there being no warrant in Scripture for <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops;</hi> but onely from the practice of after-times, whereby they were, by men onely, called to that height, we ſee no neceſſity of their <hi>Conſecration;</hi> no more doth our Church; for that it makes the ſame <hi>Conſecration</hi> which is for Biſhops, to ſerve for Archbiſhops. Upon this account, we ſee no reaſon why a ſolemn Oath of Canonical Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Archbiſhop, ſhould then be adminiſtred to every perſon that is to be Biſhop. The Exception againſt that Expreſſion of the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> in the act of Conſecration of a Biſhop, <hi>Take the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> being ſpoken to before; here we onely make the ſame profeſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, which there we did, and ſo leave it, and proceed to the next Head of Eccleſiaſtical Government, which is <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II. <hi>Of</hi> Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction.</head>
                  <p>IT hath been of late the claim of our Biſhops to have in them the ſole power of <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical: which is now pleaded for ſo boldly and openly by their Advocates, and ſuch as aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to the ſame Office and Dignity, that it is now made (though ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry groundleſly) an Eſſential part of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> by Divine Right; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs among other, the Author of an <hi>Anſwer to a Letter ſent to Doctor</hi> Turner, to <hi>Oxford,</hi> who alledgeth ſeveral Scriptures, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116869:26"/>
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. to prove that <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction</hi> is in <hi>Biſhops onely.</hi> To the ſame effect, the Author of another Book, intituled, <hi>Church-Lands not to be ſold.</hi> So others.</p>
                  <p>But, ſeeing <hi>Biſhops</hi> can exerciſe no Juriſdiction in <hi>England,</hi> but what is allowed by the Laws of the Land, as we ſhall after make it manifeſt to every eye; we ſhall not much trouble our ſelves, at this time, with their claim by <hi>Divine Right.</hi> Howbeit, leſt they ſhould think there is nothing to be ſaid againſt it, we deſire it may be conſidered, (which is known to all that have ſeriouſly conſulted Antiquity) that in the Primitive Ages of the Church, there was no Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on exerciſed, but by the Biſhops, and their Conſiſtory of Presbyters together. Even, in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, there was, even in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time, a number of the Clergy, who acted with the Biſhop, as well as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. Thence grew (by Corruption) their Conclave of <hi>Cardinals.</hi> And, from the ſame Original, here in <hi>England,</hi> firſt, <hi>Monks;</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>Deans and Chapters,</hi> were joyned with the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to aſſiſt both in <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction:</hi> although of late times they joyned with them in neither: Such was the Pride of the one, and the Idleneſs of the other. Which laſt, his late Majeſty was content to part withal. They being of no uſe, but onely to confirm Grants of the Biſhop; as he, confirmed theirs: keeping ſundry Benefices of Cure in their hands, and ſeldome or never reſiding on them; under pretence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence near the Biſhop; whereas the Canons of 1603. require them to reſide on their <hi>Benefices with Cure, all but the ſpace of one moneth in the year</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Can. 44.</note>, unleſs he be a <hi>Dean, Maſter, Warden, or chief Governour of a Cathedral, or Church,</hi> who, by <hi>Can.</hi> 42. is to reſide there, ninety days, <hi>Conjunctim</hi> or <hi>Diviſim.</hi> This is ſpoken not to juſtifie the Continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Deans</hi> and <hi>Chapters;</hi> or, to move for reducing them to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient courſe of corrupt times, in making them alone to be the Adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Biſhops: for <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> is as proper to all the Presbytery, as to thoſe Cathedral Presbyters. But we urge it, meerly and onely to demonſtrate the falſhood of that upſtart Aſſertion, that <hi>Biſhops have ſole power of Juriſdiction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And that we may contract our ſelves within neceſſary brevity (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering to whom we make our Addreſs) we ſhall give but one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance more; and that ſhall be out of the Book of <hi>Ordination,</hi> in the <hi>Ordering of Prieſts.</hi> Where, among other <hi>Queſtions</hi> propounded by the Biſhop to him that is to be <hi>ordained</hi> Prieſt, this is one; <hi>Will you reverently obey your Ordinary, and other chief Miniſters, unto whom the Government and Charge is committed over you; following with a glad mind and will their godly Admonition, and ſubmitting your ſelf to their godly Judgements?</hi> To this each of them that are to be ordained, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, <hi>I will ſo do, the Lord being my helper.</hi> By this it is evident, that more, beſide Biſhops, have power of Juriſdiction. If it be ſaid,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116869:27"/>this may be meant of <hi>ARchdeacons, Deans,</hi> &amp;c. that have it under the Biſhop: what is this to the intituling of all Miniſters thereunto? It is anſwered out of the <hi>Rubrick</hi> before the <hi>Communion,</hi> whereby eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Curate is authorized to keep off from that Sacrament, <hi>every open and notorious Liver,</hi> by whom <hi>the Congregation is offended, until he have openly declared himſelf to have truely repented, and amended his former wicked life, that the Congregation may thereby be ſatisfied.</hi> Yea, where he finds <hi>hatred and variance,</hi> he is to ſuſpend from the Sacrament, the party refuſing to be reconciled to the other, and <hi>be content to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give from the bottom of his heart, all that the other hath tranſgreſſed againſt him, and to make amends for that he himſelf hath offended.</hi> What is this, but as much and as high Juriſdiction as any Biſhop can uſe in that particular?</p>
                  <p>If this ſuffice not, take one paſſage more. In the ſame Book of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> in the <hi>Ordering</hi> of <hi>Prieſts.</hi> The <hi>Biſhop</hi> asketh every perſon whom he ordaineth a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> this Queſtion; <hi>Will you give your faithful diligence always ſo to miniſter the Doctrine and Sacraments, and the DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SCIPLINE of Chriſt, as the Lord hath commanded, and as this Realm hath received the ſame?</hi> &amp;c. To which, each Prieſt is to anſwer, <hi>I will ſo do, by the help of the Lord.</hi> What can be a more clear evidence of the intention of our Church in the firſt Reformation, then to admit all <hi>Presbyters</hi> to have a ſhare in Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, and in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of it?</p>
                  <p>How long Biſhops and others under them, have had Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Conſiſtories</hi> to exerciſe Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> to us is not certain. Yet it appeareth by Sir <hi>Edw. Cook,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Inſtit. ca. 53. p. 2259.</note> that <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror was the firſt that, by his <hi>Charter</hi> to the <hi>Dean and Chapter of</hi> Lincoln, did prohibit Sheriffs, in their <hi>Tourne</hi> Courts (wherein, before-time, all Eccleſiaſtical matters were heard, and determined) to intermedle any more with Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes, but leave them to the Biſhops. Thence, ſome conclude, that Biſhops have held Courts ever ſince <hi>William</hi> 1. Others, finding no inrollment of that <hi>Charter,</hi> until 2 <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. will not admit of ſo great Antiquity thereof. And the ſame Sir <hi>Edw. Cook</hi> there alledgeth the <hi>Red Book</hi> of <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. <hi>De general. Placitis Comitatuum,</hi> Cap. 8. extant in the Office of the <hi>Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memb.</hi> in the <hi>Exchequer,</hi> wherein, in the Sheriffs <hi>Tourne Court,</hi> is ſaid, <hi>Ibi agantur primo debita verè Chriſtianitatis jura: Secundo, Regis placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta; poſtremo, cauſae ſingulorum dignis ſatisfactionibus expleantur.</hi> There, let be handled, firſt, all due Laws of Chriſtianity, (or, <hi>Court-Chriſtian.</hi>) Secondly, Pleas of the King. Laſtly, Cauſes of particular perſons, &amp;c. <hi>Whereupon they</hi> (that is, others) <hi>conclude that Eccleſiaſtical cauſes were handled in the Tourn,</hi> in <hi>H.</hi> 1. <hi>long after the ſaid</hi> ſuppoſed <hi>Charter.</hi> Then he addeth, <hi>And certain it is, the Biſhops Conſiſtories were erected, and cauſes Eccleſiaſtical removed from the Tourn to the Conſiſtory after the making of the ſaid Red Book.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116869:27"/>
                  <p>But, let the Antiquity thereof, be what it will; it is moſt certain, that however the Popes and their Agents did often intrude, and uſurp Authority within this Realm, yet the King and Parliament ever held the Biſhops and Clergy of <hi>England</hi> within the verge of the Laws of the Land; never permitting them, either by colour of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or otherwiſe, to exerciſe any Authority, but with ſubmiſſion to the Municipal Laws. So that, whoever ſhall endeavour to put them into any further power, (in caſe they have a mind to reſtore them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Juriſdictions) doth put to his hand to make them ſo many Popes; which this Realm, even in times of Popiſh Religion here, would never endure.</p>
                  <p>And whereas ſome are pleaſed to affirm, that by the Statute of 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. there was a ſtricter reſtraint laid upon the Biſhops and Clergy, than in the times before, when they ſate in Convocation, <hi>viz.</hi> No Canons ſhould be made and put in exerciſe, that were <hi>contrariant or repugnant</hi> to the Laws of the Land: it is manifeſt that the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation was long before ſet upon them. For Sir <hi>Edw. Cook (ibid,</hi> cap. 74. pag. 323.) ſaith, That the <hi>King did often appoint Commiſſioners by Writ, to ſit with them at the Convecation, and to have cognizance of ſuch things as they meant to eſtabliſh, that nothing ſhould be done in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> &amp;c. and for this he citeth 51. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. nu. 42.46. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. prem. 8.21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.45. <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 1 <hi>Ric.</hi> 2. <hi>nu:</hi> 114. from which he concludeth, that the Statute of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8.19. <hi>is but Declaratory of the old Common Law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And, ſo ſtrict were the Kings anciently over Biſhops and Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops too, that when the Clergy <hi>petitioned in Parliament</hi> (51. Edw. 3.
<note place="margin">4 Inſtit. ca. 74. <hi>of Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</hi> p. 339.</note> num. 83.) <hi>that of every Conſultation conditional, the Ordinary may of himſelf take upon him the true underſtanding thereof, and therein proceed accordingly,</hi> (that is, without appeal to the King, whereupon <hi>Delegates</hi> by Commiſſion under the Great Seal, might hear and determine the ſame.) <hi>The Kings anſwer was, that the King cannot depart with his right, but to yeeld to his Subjects according to Law.</hi> To which Sir <hi>Edw. Cook</hi> ſubjoyns an <hi>Item</hi> to all. his Readers, <hi>Nota hoc, &amp; ſtude bene.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, this is not all. For, ſo far did the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> engage in the over-ruling of Biſhops, that they did not onely limit their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, but allowed them not liberty to make a Will without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence from the King, till they made compoſition with him; as the ſame Author telleth us, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 338</note> 
                     <hi>It appears by many Records in the reigns of</hi> H. 3. Edw. 1. <hi>(as taking ſome one or two examples for many) that by the Law and cuſtome of</hi> England, <hi>no Biſhop could make his Will of his Goods or Chattels coming of his Biſhoprick,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>without the Kings li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. The Biſhops, that they might freely make their Wills, yeelded to give to the King, after their deceaſes reſpectively for ever, ſix things:</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:116869:28"/>1. <hi>Their beſt Horſe, or Palfrrce, with Bridle and Saddle.</hi> 2. <hi>A Cloke with a Cape.</hi> 3. <hi>One Cup with a Cover.</hi> 4. <hi>One Baſon and Ewre.</hi> 5. <hi>One Ring of Gold.</hi> 6. <hi>His Kennel of Hounds. For theſe, a Writ iſſueth out of the Exchequer after the deceaſe of every Biſhop.</hi> Whether this be ſtill in uſe, we meddle not; but mention it, onely to ſhew what a ſtrict eye our Kings have ever had upon Biſhops, ſo as the Law allows them not power ſo much as of their own perſonal Eſtates, much leſs of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, without the King.</p>
                  <p>What power they had in the <hi>High Commiſſion Court,</hi> is needleſs to mention, the Court being happily laid aſide by the Statute of 17 <hi>Car.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. But, whereas they inſiſted upon <hi>ſole Juriſdiction,</hi> and now begin to exerciſe it; or at leaſt, to renew their claim thereunto, it is very well known, that by the Statute of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.2. they could hold no Courts, but in the Kings name; nor that, without Commiſſion under the Great Seal: which power was indeed revived and re-eſtabliſhed by the Act of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> after it had been repealed 1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. Howbeit, all that power is again repealed, and made void for ever, by the ſame Act of 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. and now, no Commiſſions to be granted them any more. To make this out, we ſhall rehearſe the words of both thoſe Acts of Parliament, which run thus:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Act of 1. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1. having firſt <hi>united and annexed all Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction</hi> to the Imperial Crown of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> it after addeth what power ſhall be given by <hi>Commiſſion</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Great Seal,</hi> to exerciſe the ſame, in this following Clauſe one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>viz. And that your Highneſs, your Heirs and Succeſſors, Kings or Queens of this Realm, ſhall have full Power and Authority by vertue of this Act, by Letters patents under the Great Seal of</hi> England, <hi>to aſſigne, name and authorize, when, and as often as your Highneſs, your Heirs or Succeſſors, ſhall think meet and convenient, and for ſuch and ſo long time as ſhall pleaſe your Highneſs, your Heirs or Succeſſors, ſuch perſon or perſons being natural born Subjects to your Highneſs, your Heirs or Succeſſors, as your Majeſty, your Heirs or Succeſſors, ſhall think meet, to exerciſe and uſe, occupy and execute, under your Highneſs, your Heirs and Succeſſors, all manner of Juriſdictions, Priviledges, and Preheminencies, in any wiſe touching or concerning any Spiritual or Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, within theſe your Realms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>or any other your Highneſſes Dominions and Countries. And to viſit, reform, redreſs, order, correct and amend all ſuch Errors, Hereſies, Schiſms, Abuſes, Offences, Contempts and Enormities whatſoever, which by any manner Spiritual or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Power, Authority or Juriſdiction, can, or may lawfully be reformed, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, redreſſed, corrected, reſtrained or amended, to the pleaſure of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, the increaſe of Vertue, and the Conſervation of the Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of this Realm. And that ſuch perſon or perſons ſo to be named, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, authorized, and appointed by your Highneſs, your Heirs or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116869:28"/>after the ſaid Letters Patents to him or them made and deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as is aforeſaid, ſhall have full power and authority by vertue of this Act, and of the ſaid Letters Patents, under your Highneſs, your Heirs or Succeſſours, to exerciſe, uſe, and execute all the premiſes, according to the tenour and effect of the ſaid Letters Patents: any matter, or cauſe to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi> This is one entire Clauſe of that Act; nor is there any Branch or Clauſe in that whole Act that gives more, or other Juriſdiction to Biſhops, or any other Eccleſiaſtical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Now the Act of 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1.11. having repeted this <hi>Clauſe</hi> at large, addeth, <hi>Be it Enacted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, and the Lords and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the ſame, That the aforeſaid Branch, Clauſe, Article, or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, contained in the ſaid Act, and every word, matter and thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in that Branch, Clauſe, Article, or Sentence, ſhall from henceforth be repealed, annulled, revoked, annihilated and utterly made void for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, any thing in the ſaid Act to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi> This (as we humbly conceive) puts a period to all Eccleſiaſtical Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of <hi>Biſhops, Deans</hi> and <hi>Chapters,</hi> and <hi>Archdeacons,</hi> whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>And even before that Act, of 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. that Government which they exerciſed was without; yea, contrary to Law. For, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by the Statute of 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.2. it was Enacted that <hi>all Summons and Citations, or other proceſs Eccleſiaſtical, in all Suits and Cauſes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhould from the firſt day of July thence next following be made in the name, and with the ſtile of the King, as it is in Writs Original, or Judicial at the Common Law. And that the</hi> Teſte <hi>thereof be in the name of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, or Biſhop, or other having Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, who hath the Commiſſion</hi> and grant of the Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Authority immediately from the Kings Highneſs. And that his Commiſſary, Official, or Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute exerciſing juriſdiction under him, ſhall put his name in the Citation, or Proceſs, after the</hi> Teſte. And that they, <hi>in all Seals of their Office ſhall have the Kings Highneſs Arms, decently ſet, with certain Characters under the Arms, for the knowledge of the Dioceſs, and ſhall uſe no other Seal of Juriſdiction,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>upon pain of his Majeſties diſpleaſure, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment during his Majeſties pleaſure</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">So alſo it is Enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.12. that they ſhould make their Proceſs and Writings in the Ks. name, and not under their own names; and that their Seals ſhould be the Kings Arms.</note>.</p>
                  <p>In which Act nevertheleſs, they were allowed to uſe their own Seals, in admiſſion and ordering all their own <hi>Officers,</hi> in all <hi>Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates,</hi> in <hi>all Collations, Preſentations, Inſtitutions, and Inductions of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, Letters of Orders, or Dimiſſories,</hi> as formerly was accuſtomed.</p>
                  <p>But, under colour of this laſt Toleration, they have uſed their own <hi>Names,</hi> and <hi>Seals</hi> onely, in all Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Juriſdictions,</hi> for many years laſt <hi>paſt,</hi> without taking the leaſt notice of King or Queen, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any ſpecial Commiſſion from them, for ought hath appeared in any of their pretendedly juridical proceedings, which are therefore
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:116869:29"/>apprehended to be all void in Law, albeit they had obtained, in ſecret, Letters, Patents ſo to act as they have done. For that Statute being repealed in 1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2. was again, in general terms revived and re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. and never ſince made void.</p>
                  <p>And whereas our Biſhops and Archbiſhops in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> are in all but twenty ſix in number, which being far too few to be able to execute the Office of Biſhops, as by the Word of God they are bound to do, there was in the 26th year of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. an Act of Parliament made for adding ſix and twenty <hi>Suffragan Biſhops</hi> more unto them; which that Statute ſaith, <hi>hath been accuſtomed to be had in this Realm.</hi> It was Enacted, that <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tford, Ipſwich, Colcheſter, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Gilford, Southhampton, Taunton, Shaftsbury, Molton, Marleborough, Bedford, Leiceſter, Gloceſter, Shrewsbury, Briſtol, Penreth, Bridgwater, Notingham, Grantham, Hull, Huntington, Cambridge,</hi> and the Town of <hi>Pereth,</hi> and <hi>Barwick,</hi> St. <hi>Germans</hi> in <hi>Cornwal,</hi> and the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight ſhall be taken and accepted for Sees of Biſhops Suffragans to be made in this Realm.</hi> Theſe to be choſen thus: Every Archbiſhop and Biſhop that would have <hi>Suffragans,</hi> muſt for each place nominate two perſons to the King, whereof the King to chuſe one, and to give him <hi>the name, title, and dignity of Biſhop</hi> of ſuch of the Sees aforeſaid, as he ſhould be nominated unto, and he to be called <hi>Biſhop Suffragan</hi> of that See. And the King by his Letters Patents, is to preſent him to the Archbiſhop of the Province, where this Suffragan is to be; requiring the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop (with two Biſhops or Suffragans more, to be procured by the Biſhop that names him) to <hi>Conſecrate</hi> the ſaid perſon, to the <hi>ſame name, title, ſtile and dignity</hi> of Biſhop, as to the Office of a <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhop Suffragan</hi> appertaineth: and then to execute ſuch power and authority as by the Archbiſhop, or Biſhop within whoſe Dioceſs he is to be, he ſhall be Commiſſionated to do, but no other, under pain of a <hi>Premunire;</hi> but not to partake any of the Profits of the Biſhoprick of the Dioceſs.</p>
                  <p>But our Biſhops like none of this, although heretofore uſed: which Act, being repealed by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> was revived in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. by name, and is ſtill in force. Therefore, in ſtead of twenty ſix Biſhops, to deſire fifty two, is no Puritanical requeſt, but a legal and juſt demand. For there are ſo many allowed by Law already. Yea, if two hundred Biſhops ſhould be ſetled in <hi>England,</hi> they would be too few to execute all the duties which, by the Word, are incumbent on a Biſhop. And verily, we are perſwaded in Conſcience, that this muſt be done, if there be any due care of Souls, by ſuch as have power to do it, if Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy be again ſet up in <hi>England.</hi> And we ſpeak thus, becauſe we apprehend, that by Act of Parliament all their power and juriſdiction is abſolutely taken away; and therefore, by conſequent, the Office it ſelf, although the Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament of <hi>October</hi> 9. 1646. had never been. For when their power of <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> is gone
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116869:29"/>
                     <hi>for ever,</hi> what, of the Office of a Biſhop, as ſuch, remaineth? This was the ſenſe of both Houſes of Parliament, as appears by that <hi>Ordinance</hi> which makes all their Grants ſince 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. to be null and void, becauſe their Office then expired.</p>
                  <p>If it ſhall be thought fit to ſet up <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> again, We moſt humbly pray, that it may be no other but that Primitive Epiſcopacy, agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Apoſtles rules, in that form, method and power mentioned in the Book of <hi>Reduction of Epiſcopacy,</hi> compoſed and publiſhed in the year 1641. by Dr. <hi>James <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher late Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Armagh:</hi> always provided, that there be ſuch a competent number of Biſhops ſet up, as may be able faithfully and profitably to diſcharge the Office of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> according to the mind of Chriſt expreſſed in his Word.</p>
                  <p>If the late Epiſcopal Party ſhall pretend and plead, that unleſs Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops be reſtored to all their power and pomp they arrogated before 17. <hi>Car.</hi> they ſhall not be able to do his Majeſty that ſervice which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they might, if ſo reſtored. To this it is anſwered, 1. That if they mean thereby, that they cannot do his Majeſty ſervice in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, unleſs they be reſtored to their Lordſhips again, and re-admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Houſe of Peers;</hi> we cannot think, but that there be Noble Lords enow left in that Honourable Houſe, who are far more able to do his Majeſty ſervice, then the Biſhops can do there. 2. Whereas the Biſhops and Clergy obtained a Command and Charter from <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> 1. to exclude the Sheriff and the reſt of the Laity from medling with matters Eccleſiaſtical, in their Courts (as was before ſhewed) we ſee no reaſon why Biſhops (excluded in 17. <hi>Car.</hi> 1. his reign) ſhould be again admitted to intermeddle in the Supreme Court and Judicatory of the Realm, in Civil Affairs. 3. If they be confined to the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Conſtitution, and more Biſhops made, they will be in a capacity of doing God, and his Majeſty more and better ſervice, in a more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and circumſpect Government of the Church, then ever yet they have done, or were able to do. By all which it appeareth, that if they labour to recover their former power, the pretence of doing his Majeſty <hi>better ſervice,</hi> is but to make way to their own Greatneſs, and to render them leſs able to ſerve God or the King, as in that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice they ought. Nor will his Majeſties intereſt in the Clergy be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed by making more Biſhops (without an election by a <hi>Dean and Chapter</hi>) but much increaſed, if by Act of Parliament the ſame Courſe be taken for the election of all Biſhops, which by the <hi>Statute</hi> of 26. <hi>H.</hi> 8.14. is appointed for the conſtituting of <hi>Biſhops Suffragan:</hi> and their power of <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> ſet out unto them by the King and Parliament, as it was in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> at what time, the <hi>Articles</hi> to be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in all their <hi>Viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tations,</hi> were ſet forth by the <hi>Queen,</hi> &amp;c. are yet extant, with her <hi>Injunctions.</hi> Hereby alſo his Majeſty would be ſure to have a far greater influence into all the Clergy of note, by how
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:116869:30"/>much the more the number of Biſhops is increaſed, and more learned men, made capable of ſuch preferments; which a quarter of them can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, if Epiſcopacy be confined to twenty ſix Biſhops.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III. <hi>Of</hi> DISCIPLINE.</head>
                  <p>HAving ſpoken of the <hi>Subject,</hi> or Perſons in whom the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction,</hi> by the Laws of the Realm, reſided; we proceed to offer ſomewhat touching the <hi>Rules</hi> or Laws for execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, under this Head of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> which containeth the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> or Rules, to wit, the <hi>Kings Eccleſiaſtical Laws,</hi> by which alone all perſons truſted with Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, have been enabled to exerciſe that Government.</p>
                  <p>How that <hi>Diſcipline</hi> is bounded, appeareth in and by the Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſtill in force, in 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8.19. and 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. which bounds, a great <hi>Scioliſt</hi> is pleaſed to call <hi>ſad reſtrictions and limitations</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">D. <hi>Heylin, Certam. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtol.</hi> pag. 89. which ſheweth how they like the Laws, and how far, they would go, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Laws, if they durſt.</note>. The bounds in the former Act are theſe. 1. That none of the Clergy ſhould <hi>from thence forth, preſume to attempt, alledge, claim, or put in ure any Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Ordinances Provincial, or Synodals, or any other Canons; Nor, ſhall enact, promulge, or execute any ſuch Canons, Conſtitutions, or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances Provincial, by whatſoever name, or names they may be called in their Convocations, in time coming (which always ſhall be aſſembled by Authority of the Kings Writ) unleſs the ſame Clergy may have the Kings moſt Royal Aſſent, and Licenſe, to make, promulge, and execute ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Conſtitutions, and Ordinances Provincial, or Synodal, upon pain of every one of the ſaid Clergy, doing contrary to this Act; and being thereof convict, to ſuffer impriſonment, and make Fine at the Kings Will.</hi> It is true, that, at the ſuit of the then <hi>Clergy, divers Conſtitutions, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and Canons Provincial, or Synodal, which heretofore had been Enacted, and then thought to be not only much prejudicial to the Kings Prerogative royal, and repugnant to the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, but alſo over-much onerous to his Highneſs Subjects:</hi> by that Act, the King was to chuſe thirty two Perſons, to review, approve, or reject the ſame; which being begun, but not perfected by the time limited, ſo as to get the <hi>Royal Aſſent</hi> thereunto,
<note place="margin">3.4. Edw. 6. cap. 11.</note> that Act revived in 3.4. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. authorizing him to chuſe thirty two Perſons, to perfect that work. The perſons were choſen, they did the work, compiled a Book intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Reformatio Legum Eccleſiaſticarum,</hi> yet extant: but for lack of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:116869:30"/>the Royal Aſſent thereunto, within the time prefixed, that Act expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and, their Book of <hi>Reformation,</hi> with it: which was never ſince renewed.</p>
                  <p>In the Act of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8.19. it is <hi>provided,</hi> that <hi>ſuch Canons, Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Ordinances, and Synodals Provincial being already made,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>El.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>which be not contrariant, nor repugnant to the Laws, Statutes and Cuſtomes of this Realm; nor to the damage or hurt of the Kings Prerogative-Royal, ſhall now ſtill be uſed and executed as they were before the making of this Act, till ſuch time as they be viewed, ſearched, or otherwiſe ordered &amp; determined by the ſaid thirty two perſons, or the more part of them, according to the tenor, form and effect of this preſent Act.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By occaſion hereof, Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Ubi ſupra.</note> affirmeth, that ſo much of the Popes <hi>Canon-Law,</hi> (firſt intended for the Church in general) as is not contrary to the Laws, Cuſtoms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Land, is ſtill in force, in our Courts Eccleſiaſtical, as the Civil or Imperial Laws are, in our Courts of <hi>Admiralty,</hi> and <hi>Prerogative,</hi> for <hi>probate of Wills.</hi> But we humbly conceive this cannot be ſo, becauſe however the Civil Law is ſtill in uſe in <hi>maritine,</hi> and <hi>Teſtamentary</hi> Affairs, in regard that Forrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as well as Natives, are, or may be therein concerned; and ſo thoſe Civil Laws are permitted; not, in relation to the <hi>Emperour,</hi> but as the Law of Nations, which never was by any Act of Parliament, in thoſe eaſes, prohibited in <hi>England.</hi> The Popes Canon-Law, on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is ever ſince diſabled by the Statute of 24. <hi>H.</hi> 8.12. and by that Act before-mentioned, is wholly abrogated, and null. For, if his power be renounced, can his Laws (which are the chief part of a Law-givers power) be ſtill in force; eſpecially, where no Canons, but ſuch as have the <hi>Royal Aſſent,</hi> may be uſed in <hi>England?</hi> And if that might be admitted, yet that very <hi>Proviſo,</hi> in the Statute of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8.19. puts a period to it, after the time the thirty two perſons, or major part of them, did view and ſearch them, and drew up a Body of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Laws to be uſed here, (which the ſame Doctor confeſſeth they did) although the want of the Kings <hi>Aſſent,</hi> made it not valid in Law. For, the Proviſo doth not ſay, the old Canons ſhall be uſed till the King <hi>Aſſent;</hi> but, onely <hi>till ſuch time as they be viewed, ſearched;</hi> or, <hi>otherwiſe ordered and determined by them, or the more part of them.</hi> Nor doth that Act in any Clauſe, mention any other <hi>Canons or Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,</hi> but ſuch as are <hi>Provincial,</hi> or called by other names, always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and mentioned to be made in <hi>Convocations</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> not in the <hi>Popes Conclave.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to the end it may yet further appear, that he who ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently taketh upon him to improve his knowledge to whom he wrote that Epiſtle, hath miſ-informed him, and wreſted the Laws alſo; take notice, that the <hi>Canon-Laws</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> are onely ſuch as are, or have been made in <hi>England.</hi> Theſe are of two ſorts; <hi>legatine,</hi> or
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116869:31"/>
                     <hi>Provincial.</hi> The <hi>Legatine</hi> were, 77 <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, 26 were made by <hi>Otho</hi> the Popes <hi>Legate,</hi> Preſident of a Synod here in <hi>England;</hi> the other, 51. in another Synod, after holden under <hi>Othobone,</hi> Legate of the Pope in 32. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. An. 1248. The <hi>Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial</hi> Conſtitutions were ſuch as, in ſeveral places of <hi>England,</hi> were made under the Archbiſhops of <hi>Canterbury:</hi> in all, 212. whereof the firſt 48. were made under <hi>Stephen Langhton,</hi> in the reign of King <hi>John;</hi> and the laſt three, were made under <hi>Henry Chichley,</hi> in the reign of <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. Theſe <hi>Provincial</hi> Conſtitutions, about the year 1422. were digeſted into a Body by <hi>William Lindwood,</hi> who alſo wrote a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon them; the other, by <hi>Johannes de Aton,</hi> Canon of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln,</hi> who likewiſe Commented upon them: all which, are yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</p>
                  <p>Now, we muſt underſtand, the Act of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8.19. ſpeaks onely of <hi>Canons, Conſtitutions, Ordinances Provincial, or other, or by whatſoever name they be called in their</hi> CONVOCATION. Theſe, and no other, were to be reviewed; and, out of theſe, ſuch as by the thirty two perſons choſen by <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. or <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. ſhould be <hi>viewed, order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and <hi>determined</hi> to ſtand, were onely to be in force, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to every impartial eye that ſhall conſult the Statute. And theſe, having been in 4. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. viewed; and, thereupon, by <hi>Gualter Haddon,</hi> under Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and four <hi>Claſſes</hi> into which the ſaid thirty two perſons were divided, that Book, called, <hi>Reformatio Legum Eccleſiaſticarum,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Preface</hi> thereunto) were compiled. And theſe being ſo compoſed, and publiſhed, that all might object what they could (if they had ought) againſt them, before Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the King died before his Royal Aſſent was given; and ſo, they never were confirmed. But yet, the very <hi>viewing, ordering,</hi> and <hi>deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining</hi> of thoſe old Conſtitutions, (be they what they could) were, by the cloſing <hi>Proviſo</hi> forementioned, in 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8. all void, and of none effect.</p>
                  <p>And, albeit divers <hi>Canons,</hi> or <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> were made in Q. <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths</hi> reign, (beſide thoſe <hi>Injunctions,</hi> and <hi>Articles</hi> for <hi>Viſitations,</hi> in her firſt year) yet none of them being (for ought we know) confirmed by the Royal Aſſent, under the <hi>Great Seal,</hi> are now, by any, reputed Obligatory. It be then onely the <hi>Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, treated upon by the Biſhop of</hi> London, <hi>Preſident of the Convocation for the Province of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and the reſt of the Biſhops and Clergy of the ſaid Province; and, agreed upon with the Kings Majeſties licence in that Synod begun at</hi> London, An. Dom. 1603. in the firſt year of King <hi>James</hi> his reign over <hi>England;</hi> and, after publiſhed by his ſaid Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Authority, under the <hi>Great Seal of England:</hi> which can now be ſo much as pretended to be of any force.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:116869:31"/>
                  <p>And here, we ſhall not diſpute their validity, after that Kings death' they being not after re-eſtabliſhed by King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt: but, we ſhall onely ſpeak to the Legality of them, as they were once ratified; and as they are any of them <hi>contrariant and repugnant</hi> to the <hi>Laws</hi> or <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> of the Land. As for <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> (which the Statute of 25. <hi>H.</hi> 8.19. referreth to, as well as to the <hi>Laws</hi>) we ſhall ſay little, becauſe this is more proper for Lawyers, upon Prohibitions, granted out of his Majeſties Civil Courts, to confider, and debate. We therefore conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Canons,</hi> or ſuch of them onely as are <hi>repugnant</hi> to any of the <hi>Laws</hi> in force.</p>
                  <p>This is a large Field: Thoſe Canons being no leſs than 141. in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which are more then heretofore were ever made in any three <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods</hi> (by whomſoever held) in <hi>England.</hi> We ſhall therefore keep one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuch as we find moſt contrariant to thoſe Laws, which we are in duty bound chiefly to take notice of. As for inſtance.</p>
                  <p>Of thoſe twelve <hi>Canons,</hi> under the firſt Head or Title, <hi>viz. Of the Church of</hi> England, there be eleven of them, the breach of any of which, is to be puniſhed with <hi>Excommunication</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>not to be revoked till ſuch as breake them, after repent, and publickly revoke their wicked errours.</hi> The perſons to be excommunicated, are, I. <hi>Impugners of the Kings Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy:</hi> Can. 2. II. All that <hi>affirm the Church of</hi> England <hi>is not a true and Apoſtolical Church, teaching and maintaining the Doctrine of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles:</hi> Can. 3. where, it is not defined what <hi>the Church of</hi> England <hi>is.</hi> III. <hi>Impugners of the publick Worſhip of God, eſtabliſhed:</hi> Can. 4. which few know to be <hi>eſtabliſhed.</hi> IV. <hi>Impugners of the Articles of Religion, agreed upon,</hi> 1562. Can. 5. the eſtabliſhment whereof, is doubtful. V. <hi>Impugners of the Rites and Ceremonies eſtabliſhed,</hi> Can. 6. of which there is no certainty. VI. <hi>Impugners of the Government of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>by Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. Can. 7. there being none ſuch. VII. <hi>Impugners of the form of conſecrating and ordering Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. or <hi>that any thing in it is repugnant to the Word of God,</hi> Can. 8. there being in the form no ſuch Words as <hi>ordering of Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Biſhops:</hi> and it having been made out that there be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions in it; one of which, is repugnant to the Word. VIII. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of Schiſm:</hi> Can. 9. IX. Maintainers of (ſuch as the Canons call) <hi>Schiſmaticks:</hi> that is, who affirm ſuch Miniſters as <hi>refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Book of Common-prayer,</hi> &amp;c. Can. 10. which is hard to prove. X. <hi>Maintainers of Conventicles:</hi> Can. 11. that is, of ſuch as maintain that <hi>there are in</hi> England, <hi>other Meetings, Aſſemblies, or Congregations of the Kings born Subjects, then ſuch as by the Laws are allowed, which may rightly claim the name of true and lawful Churches.</hi> XI. <hi>Maintainers of Conſtitutions made in Conventicles, without the Kings Authority; and, ſubmit to them:</hi> Can. 12. So all the <hi>Rules</hi> confirmed by Parliament, for <hi>Church-Government,</hi> make the Parliament lyable to Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116869:32"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:116869:32"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:116869:33"/>and the Aſſemby too, and all the Presbyterians in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides theſe, there is, <hi>Can.</hi> 59. for excommunicating <hi>Miniſters</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to <hi>Catechiſe every Sunday,</hi> after a third offence herein complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of. So, <hi>Can.</hi> 68. decreeth <hi>Miniſters refuſing to Chriſten, or Bury,</hi> to be excommunicated <hi>Majori Excommunicatione.</hi> And <hi>Canon</hi> 72. ordaineth that if a Miniſter, without Licenſe from the Biſhop, under his hand and ſeal, appoint or keep faſts, or <hi>be preſent at them, either publiquely, or in any private Houſes, other then ſuch as by Law, are, or by publique Authority ſhall be appointed,</hi> he ſhall for the firſt offence be <hi>ſuſpended;</hi> for the ſecond, <hi>excommunicated;</hi> and, for the third, <hi>depoſed</hi> from the Miniſtry. Laſtly, the 73. <hi>Canon,</hi> excommunicateth <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> all <hi>Miniſters</hi> and others <hi>meeting in any private houſe, or elſewhere</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">What, if in <hi>Parliament;</hi> or, in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation?</hi>
                     </note>, <hi>to conſult upon any matter or courſe to be taken by them, or upon their motion or direction by any other, which may any way tend to the impeaching or depraving of the Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>or of the Book of Common-prayer, or of any part of the diſcipline now eſtabliſhed.</hi> What is that?</p>
                  <p>Now, this ſentence of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> being to be pronounced by a Miniſter onely, and, after to be publiquely denounced by other Miniſters; and the perſons excommunicated upon the 2, 3, 4, 5, 9, and 11th Canons, not to be reſtored but by the <hi>Archbiſhop;</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch perſon (not reſtored) is liable to the Writ <hi>De excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato capiendo;</hi> (or elſe the excommunication ſignifies nothing) we appeal to all whether theſe <hi>Canons</hi> (if executed) be not againſt the <hi>Stat.</hi> of 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 23. which Enacteth, that if, in the <hi>Significavit</hi> (of the Ordinary) for obtaining a Writ <hi>de excom. capiend. it be not contained, that the excommunication doth proceed upon ſome cauſe or contempt of ſome original matter of Hereſie, or refuſing to have his or their child ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptized, or to receive the holy Communion as it is now commonly uſed to be received in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>or to come to Divine-ſervice now commonly uſed in the ſaid Church of</hi> England, <hi>or Errour in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or Doctrine now received or allowed in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, Simony, Perjury in the Eccleſiaſtical Court, or Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try;</hi> Then all ſuch <hi>Writs,</hi> and <hi>Significavits</hi> to be <hi>void in Law.</hi> And whether ſuch Miniſters as in <hi>Court,</hi> or in Churches, pronounce, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſuch <hi>excommunications;</hi> or, for <hi>non-appearance, non-payment of Fees,</hi> &amp;c. (too too commonly practiced in thoſe late Courts,) be not lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be puniſhed, by an Action at Law, for doing ſuch illegal Acts, as are not juſtifiable by the Laws of the Land: Or, if ſuch a Writ will lye againſt any man for <hi>Hereſie,</hi> (not declared ſuch by Parliament ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.) for <hi>not receiving the Communion, kneeling;</hi> or, for <hi>not coming to the Common-prayer;</hi> as now <hi>uſed</hi> (it being already made out that it is not eſtabliſhed by Law;) or, for diſſenting from any of the <hi>Articles of Religion</hi> of <hi>An.</hi> 1562. (when it hath been ſhewed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116869:33"/>that ſome of them are <hi>doubtful,</hi> ſome <hi>defective,</hi> and diſagreeing from one another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) is it not high time to <hi>Reform</hi> theſe things; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, when by the <hi>Canons,</hi> not <hi>kneeling,</hi> not coming to Common-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, are declared to be <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and any <hi>diſſent</hi> from thoſe <hi>Articles,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing adjudged <hi>errour in doctrine,</hi> the party ſhall be puniſhed with <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication;</hi> yea, with <hi>impriſonment,</hi> by <hi>Writ</hi> out of <hi>Chancery;</hi> and not be <hi>abſolved,</hi> but by the <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> (Can. 5.) nor, by him, till he ſhall have <hi>repented,</hi> and openly revoked that his <hi>diſſent,</hi> as a <hi>wicked er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour;</hi> how juſt, and neceſſary ſoever ſuch <hi>diſſent was?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, the 14th <hi>Canon</hi> appoints Divine ſervice to be ſaid, not only on the <hi>Holy-days</hi> appointed by the Book of Common-prayer, but on <hi>their Eves.</hi> Which obſervation of <hi>Eves,</hi> is taken away by the Books of Common-prayer; and ſo this Canon is herein contrary to the Act of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. Moreover, the ſame Canon enjoyneth Miniſters to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>the Orders, Rites, and Ceremonies preſcribed in the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer,</hi> which by referring to theſe in 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. admits of a <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice only,</hi> ſo doth that of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. yet this enterferes with the 58. <hi>Canon;</hi> of which, before. And whereas that 14th <hi>Canon</hi> forbids <hi>diminiſhing</hi> any part of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> in <hi>regard of preaching, or in any other reſpect, or adding any thing in the matter or form thereof;</hi> the Book of Common-prayer it ſelf, doth warrant us to <hi>diminiſh,</hi> that is, to omit all that men now call the <hi>ſecond Service;</hi> when there is no <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> as hath been alſo ſhewed.</p>
                  <p>The 17th <hi>Canon</hi> enjoyneth <hi>all Fellows, Scholars, and Students</hi> (though Boys) as well as <hi>Maſters of Colleges and Halls,</hi> upon <hi>Sundays, Holy-days</hi> and their <hi>Eves,</hi> to wear <hi>Surplices</hi> at <hi>Divine ſervice,</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for it, the <hi>Order of the Church of</hi> England: and <hi>Graduates</hi> to wear the <hi>Hoods of their degrees.</hi> Whereas the Order in the Liturgy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns Surplices only to Miniſters in <hi>the times of their Miniſtration:</hi> not to others. And this of Boys wearing <hi>Surplices,</hi> doth countenance that fond conceit ſo much cryed up in Popery, that all once entred into Colleges, ought to receive <hi>primam tonſuram,</hi> and therefore to wear <hi>Surplices</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ham. le Strange</hi> in Affin. of Div. Serv.</note>.</p>
                  <p>The 24 <hi>Canon</hi> enjoyneth <hi>Copes:</hi> which are forbidden in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> before <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> in 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. of which, before. The 27th <hi>Canon,</hi> requireth Miniſters not to <hi>adminiſter</hi> the Communion to any but ſuch as <hi>kneel,</hi> under pain of <hi>Suſpenſion;</hi> whereas, we have before demonſtrated out of 2. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. that <hi>kneeling</hi> is left arbitrary. And, if any perſon not <hi>kneeling,</hi> be refuſed the Communion, with what ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice can he be puniſhed with <hi>Excommunication</hi> (which may end in <hi>impriſonment</hi> upon a Writ <hi>De excom. cap.</hi> by vertue of the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Statute of 5. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 23.) even when he deſireth to communicate with that Liberty in geſture which the Law alloweth him? Yet, both <hi>Miniſter, Church-Wardens</hi> and <hi>Queſt-men</hi> (the Office and duty
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:116869:34"/>of which laſt, in Eccleſiaſticals, we know not) muſt take notice whether every Pariſhioner come ſo often to the Communion as the Law requireth, <hi>Can.</hi> 28. which if he do not, he is to be <hi>preſented,</hi> &amp;c. which makes way to <hi>Excommunication,</hi> and <hi>impriſonment,</hi> as aforeſaid, albeit it be not his fault that he received not: unleſs it be an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, to claim, and make uſe of the liberty which the Law affordeth him.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Explanation of the lawful uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm,</hi> undertaken in <hi>Can.</hi> 30. is very defective: for, whereas it undertakes to <hi>remove all ſcruples of</hi> Conſcience therein, it produceth not one <hi>Scripture,</hi> nor <hi>Father</hi> to that end: but only indefinitely talks of both; which, without better arguments and more diſtinct proofs, can never, in common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, quiet (much leſs ſatisfie) any mans Conſcience that maketh ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereof. Nor can we ſubmit thereto, till we ſee it proved, as well as affirmed.</p>
                  <p>The 31. <hi>Canon</hi> forbiddeth the making of any <hi>Deacons,</hi> or Miniſters, ſave only on the four Sundays after the <hi>Ember-Weeks,</hi> appointed for prayer and faſting, and ſo continued in <hi>England</hi> (by what Law, when the <hi>Stat.</hi> of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.3. declares the contrary?) and this to be done <hi>in the Cathedral, or Pariſh-church where the Biſhop reſideth,</hi> in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence not onely of the <hi>Archdeacon,</hi> but of the <hi>Dean</hi> and two <hi>Preben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries</hi> at leaſt (if not by any lawful cauſe let, or hindred) or, of <hi>four other learned and grave Perſons, Maſters of Art at the leaſt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for publique Preachers.</hi> What Law, for confining Ordination to four times a year? If there be a Law, do Biſhops now obſerve it? Is it not uſual to ordain in other mens Dioceſſes: which they can no more legally do, then a Sheriff execute his Office, when he is out of his County? How often do <hi>Deans</hi> and <hi>Prebendaries</hi> aſſiſt at Ordinations? And why muſt all other Aſſiſtants be <hi>Maſters of Arts at leaſt?</hi> What Law, or Rule for any of theſe things; unleſs, for being <hi>Aſſiſtants</hi> to, and <hi>Co-ordainers</hi> with the Biſhop; which, this <hi>Canon</hi> doth tacitely deny, when it ſaith, ſuch and ſuch ſhall be <hi>preſent:</hi> but, not a word of their <hi>Laying on of Hands,</hi> according to the Book of <hi>Ordination?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And whereas by the 36th <hi>Canon, Subſcription</hi> is enjoyned to the Books of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> and of <hi>Ordination,</hi> not only upon all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> to Benefices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which, by <hi>Can.</hi> 37. is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired alſo of all Lecturers, Catechiſts, Readers; yea, (by <hi>Can.</hi> 77.) of all <hi>School-maſters</hi> too, (unleſs to the laſt clauſe of <hi>Art.</hi> 2. touching <hi>uſing the book</hi> of Common-prayer) whereas the Statute of 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. requires no ſubſcription but to the 39. Articles: nor that, ſave only of ſuch as are to be <hi>inſtituted</hi> to a Benefice: not at <hi>Ordination,</hi> or at taking Licenſes to Preach only. The 38th <hi>Canon</hi> touching <hi>Revolters after Subſcription,</hi> hath been ſpoken to before.</p>
                  <p>The 40th <hi>Canon</hi> enjoyning an Oath againſt <hi>Simony,</hi> is neceſſary; yet,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:116869:34"/>againſt Law; and particularly, againſt <hi>the Petition of Right.</hi> This therefore we ſay no more of, but humbly pray, ſuch an Oath may be impoſed by Law. But, whereas the 49th <hi>Canon</hi> prohibiteth <hi>Miniſters</hi> not to expound Scripture, &amp;c. if not Licenſed by the Biſhop; this is expreſly contrary to Law (8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.) which confirmeth the Book of Ordination, in and by which every one ordained a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> hath the Bible delivered into his hand by the Biſhop, with theſe Words, <hi>Take thou Authority to preach the Word of God,</hi> &amp;c. Yet, muſt every ſuch ordained Miniſter be compelled to be at the charge of taking out a further Licenſe from the ſame Biſhop, at the ſame time, to preach in the ſame place; or elſe, not to perform that duty, which he promiſed ſolemnly to the Biſhop, and by him was authorized to perform, at his <hi>Ordination.</hi> Nor may any Miniſters be ſuffered (by the 51. <hi>Canon</hi>) to preach in any other Church, without <hi>ſhewing</hi> ſuch Licenſe, although otherwiſe well known to be ſufficiently authorized thereunto. And whereas the 62. <hi>Canon</hi> alloweth Miniſters to celebrate Matrimony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween other perſons, without asking the Bannes in Churches, if he have a <hi>Licenſe</hi> for doing of it from the Biſhop, Archdeacon, or their Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals; this is expreſly contradictory to the Book of Common-prayer, Rubrick 1. before <hi>the form of Matrimony:</hi> and ſo, contrary to Law, of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. if that Book be confirmed thereby.</p>
                  <p>There be ſundry other Exceptions juſtly to be taken to the Book of <hi>Canons,</hi> (as namely, to ſuch <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Offices,</hi> beſides <hi>Biſhops and Presbyters,</hi> as be admitted to bear a ſhare in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Juriſdiction; albeit they be <hi>Lay-men;</hi> while yet they abominate <hi>Lay-Elders</hi> in the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government, beſide many other) all which, we at preſent, forbear; not, as approving of them, but, as hoping for a Reformation of that as well as of other things. We therefore ſhall now only with all humility, propound a few <hi>Queries,</hi> very neceſſary, as we conceive, to be ſeriouſly conſidered.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Quere:</hi> Whether, if there be any thing of ſubſtance altered in, or added to the <hi>Articles of Religion,</hi> or Books of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> or <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination;</hi> and, thoſe <hi>Alterations,</hi> or <hi>Additions</hi> not expreſly mentioned, and confirmed by Parliament: this doth not make thoſe Books to be void in Law, if pleaded at Law? The Grounds of this <hi>Quere,</hi> are, the Acts of 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. as touching the <hi>Articles:</hi> that, of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. as to the Book of <hi>Common-prayer:</hi> and, the Statute of <hi>Eliz.</hi> 8.1. and of 5.6. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.1. as to <hi>Ordination.</hi> Which laſt named <hi>Act,</hi> ſaith, that the Books therein mentioned were annexed to the ſaid Statute; yet are they not to be found inrolled therewith: no more is the other Book of <hi>Articles,</hi> in 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> inrolled with that Act.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Quere:</hi> Whether the Statutes which are ſaid to confirm any of the things named in the former Quere, mentioning only the <hi>Titles,</hi> but not reciting the matter of the Books themſelves, do make thoſe Books, or
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:116869:35"/>the things contained in them, (which have been ſeveral times altered) although never ſo much as ſaid to be inrolled, nor found ſo to be; do make thoſe things to be eſtabliſhed and good in Law, becauſe now commonly reputed, received, and generally uſed as ratified by Law? The Ground of this <hi>Quere,</hi> is, that clauſe in 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. which after men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning ſome <hi>Alterations</hi> (but not particularly naming them) in the <hi>Common-prayer-book,</hi> prohibiteth all other <hi>Alterations,</hi> ſaying, <hi>[And none other, or otherwiſe.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Quere:</hi> If any man be indited, or ſued at Law, upon the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. for not <hi>reading</hi> of, or coming to <hi>hear</hi> the Book of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer;</hi> or, upon the Stat. of 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. for not reading the <hi>Articles</hi> of 1562: and, the Defendant plead <hi>Not guilty,</hi> and deny theſe Books to be thoſe confirmed by thoſe Laws, till the Plaintiff prove them to be of Record; whether is not the Plaintiff bound to prove that, and in the mean time, the Defendant not puniſhable by thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes? The Grounds of this <hi>Quere,</hi> are, firſt, that there are no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, of theſe to be found: ſecondly, the Books have been ſeveral times altered ſince thoſe Acts: and thirdly, many puniſhed upon the ſaid Acts, becauſe thoſe Books have been generally received and uſed as eſtabliſhed by Law.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Quere:</hi> Whether, notwithſtanding the <hi>Royal Licence</hi> before, and <hi>Aſſent</hi> after; any <hi>Canons</hi> made in <hi>Convocation,</hi> be valid in Law, before they be ratified by Act of Parliament, as the <hi>Service-book,</hi> and <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Religion</hi> were ſaid to be? and, whether, by conſequent, the <hi>Canons</hi> of 1603. be now binding? The grounds hereof, are, firſt, that all other <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> are, or are reputed to be, ratified in Parliament. Secondly, the Statute of 1. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 2. which gives power to the <hi>Queen, her Heirs and Succeſſours,</hi> to grant Licence to Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Biſhops, and others, to exerciſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction,</hi> when it ſpeaks of withdrawing, or altering any <hi>Rites and Ceremonies;</hi> or, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>new;</hi> the power is there given to the <hi>Queen</hi> alone, without men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Heirs and Succeſſours.</hi> And when any thing is ordered, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by the King, although under the Great Seal: yet the enforcing thereof (before ratification by Parliament) is held to be contrary to the <hi>Petition of Right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We ſhall now cloſe up all with this humble Advertiſement; that, whereas it is pleaded by ſome, that <hi>Liturgies</hi> (and, among them, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ours) are ancienter then the <hi>Popiſh Maſs-Books</hi> by many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years (whence they infer the weakneſs and folly of their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, who ſay, that all, or moſt, or any of the things contained in our Service-Book, are taken out of the Maſs-Book, and ſo are Popiſh, and upon that account would have them aboliſhed:) and, for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, produce ſome paſſages out of <hi>Ignatius, Clem: Alexandrinus, Juſtin Martyr, Tertullian, Cyprian, Chryſoſtome,</hi> &amp;c. wherein ſundry things in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:116869:35"/>uſe among us, are found mentioned in them; and, by ſome, the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of St. <hi>James, Peter,</hi> &amp;c. are alſo urged, although by many Learned men, cenſured as ſuppoſititious. Yet none of theſe Authors do men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any Publick Form, (the ſame for ſubſtance with ours;) although they ſpeak of Publick Prayers made in the Congregation, which none ever denyed. <hi>Publick Prayer</hi> is one thing; a Publick <hi>Form,</hi> another. Nor are we againſt all Liturgies, but onely againſt that which is liable to ſuch material Exceptions as neceſſitate us to deſire a new <hi>Form.</hi> And albeit ſome of the <hi>Rites and Ceremonies</hi> now in uſe may be mentioned in ſundry of the Fathers within the firſt 600 years after Chriſt; yet, the mentioning of them, is no evidence of the lawfulneſs of them; or, that they are not Popiſh, (although of latter times, eſpouſed by that Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of <hi>Rome</hi>) for as much as Popery was in the Egge, and <hi>the myſtery of iniquity began to work,</hi> (although under diſguiſes, and other names) even in the time of St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. Yea, ſome of thoſe very Fathers have ſundry paſſages in them, which condemn thoſe very things which are now cryed up upon the very authority of their vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable names. We ſhall, for brevity, give but one inſtance, which every Reader may find in the Preface touching <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> before the Book of Common-Prayer; which, albeit it hath been before alledged, we here briefly touch upon again, for better ſatisfaction of ſuch as cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the Author himſelf. The particular mentioned in that Preface, is a paſſage out of St. <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> who was ſo far from approving ſuch a number of <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> (yet, not to be compared with the multitude, in after-times) that he complained that hereby, <hi>Chriſtians were in worſe caſe then were the Jews,</hi> and therefore counſelled to take off that <hi>yoke and burden,</hi> ſo ſoon as it might quietly be done. And this was one of the Grounds and Reaſons there alledged, of the cutting off of ſo many ſuperſtitious Ceremonies, in the firſt Reformation, under that bleſſed King, <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth: which, of late, our <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Grotian</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines and Prelates have ſought to recal under the colour and guiſe of Antiquity: for which they produce onely ſome bits and ſcraps of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to prove their Antiquity; but, no ſolid Arguments to make out their lawfulneſs and conveniency; and yet ſeek to impoſe them on thoſe who hold themſelves bound to <hi>hate the garments ſpotted with the fleſh,</hi> as well as the <hi>fleſh,</hi> that is, the <hi>corruption</hi> it ſelf. We therefore conclude, That it is not bare Antiquity, but Divine Verity that muſt be the onely Rule and Standard of all <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip, Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Juriſdiction and Diſcipline,</hi> among all that intend Conformity to the <hi>Mind of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 2. line 7. read 4 <hi>Car.</hi> p. 7. l. 4. r. them <hi>in print</hi>) p. 34. l. 18. r. <hi>that,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. p. 43. l. 26. r. <hi>Presbyteris.</hi> l. 30. r. <hi>qui.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
